<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina militaris, or, A body of military medicines experimented by Raymundus Mindererus ... ; Englished out of High-Dutch.</title>
            <title>Medicina militaris. English</title>
            <author>Minderer, Raymund, 1570?-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20182</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12354090</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12354090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 643:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina militaris, or, A body of military medicines experimented by Raymundus Mindererus ... ; Englished out of High-Dutch.</title>
                  <title>Medicina militaris. English</title>
                  <author>Minderer, Raymund, 1570?-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 152, [12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid, and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Index: p. [1]-[12] at end.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Medicina militaris.</note>
                  <note>Previously issued as v. [3] of Paul Barbette's A complete treatise of chirurgery : containing the chirurgical and anatomical works, second edition. London : 1674. It was apparently also issued separately.</note>
                  <note>The German original was first published in Augsburg in 1620 under title: Medicina militaris, seu, Libellus castrensis ... id est : Gemaine Handstücklein zur Kriegs-Artzney gehörig.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MEDICINA MILITARIS:</hi> OR, A BODY OF MILITARY MEDICINES Experimented.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Raymundus Mindererus,</hi> Late Chief Phyſitian of the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and of the Imperial City of <hi>Auſpurg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed</hi> out of <hi>High-Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the <hi>Angel,</hi> over againſt the Little North Door of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church. 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60082:2"/>
            <head>A BODY OF <hi>MILITARY MEDICINES</hi> EXPERIMENTED.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Concerning the Morals of a Souldier.</head>
               <p>WHereas the Old Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers wiſhed to every one <hi>MENTEM SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAM IN CORPORE SANO, a Sound Mind in a Sound Body;</hi> conſidering how much it conduced to the Health of the Body to have the Mind free from Vice and Vexation: It will behoove a Souldier, as much at leaſt as any man, to endeavour after that Soundneſs and Integrity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60082:3"/>
which may inſpire him with true Fortitude, undiſturbed from the troubles and anxieties accompanying Impiety and Injuſtice. To this end, he ought, in the firſt place, be conſtant in paying his Duties to Almighty God, by ſerving Him in publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, by imploring the Divine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and bleſſing in all his Juſt undertakings, and by returning his humble acknowledgments for every good ſucceſs. Next, he ought to ſerve his Prince faithfully to the beſt of his skill and power, to obey his Officers readily, and to do to all others, as he would be done to, if he were in their condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What care a Souldier is to take of his Body.</head>
               <p>THe Mind being thus taken care of, thou art to adviſe with a skilful Phyſician concerning thy Body, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not neceſſary to purge it,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60082:3"/>
the better to ſecure thy ſelf from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and Fevers. Then furniſh thy ſelf with ſome Mithridate or Treacle, to uſe it againſt infection; taking of it in the morning faſting, againſt the ill Air, the quantity of a haſel-nut. Take alſo with thee a quantity of <hi>Zedoary, Angelica, Imperatoria</hi> or <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterwort,</hi> and <hi>Carlina;</hi> of which thou ſhalt do well, now and then to eat ſome for the preſervation of thy ſtrength, and againſt the corruption of the Air. But eſpecially keep thy Head and Feet warm, by the neglect of which thou maiſt caſt thy ſelf into great danger. Take heed of ſurchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thy ſtomach, which is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and to convey the nouriſhment for the whole body, and reſtrain as much as thou canſt thy appetite, there being nothing more hurtful to health, than when that is irregular and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant.</p>
               <p>Gird thy ſelf well, that thy body may be cloſe, and ſo be ſecured from receiving miſchief in leaping, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſtorming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thy bowels
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60082:4"/>
from being put out of their place.</p>
               <p>Take alſo with thee out of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary's ſhop a powder, called <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ſolutivus de Tribus,</hi> which is not dear. Of this, when thou needeſt purging, take the weight of a <hi>ducat</hi> or a little more, according to thy conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, in warm fleſh-broath or the like, early in the morning faſting; ſo ordering the matter, that that day thou maiſt keep thy ſelf warm in thy quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Faſt two hours after the taking of it, and then eat warm meat. The ſame may be done with <hi>Pulvis Sena Montagnana,</hi> and <hi>Pulvis ſolutivus de Tartaro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou be troubled with <hi>Corns</hi> on thy feet, apply to them every day freſh lard, and continue this, till by the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the lard they grow ſoft; and then they will fall off from the very roots without pain.</p>
               <p>To free or ſecure thy ſelf from <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> take a good quantity of Worm-wood, and the inner cuttings of horſe-hoofs, cut out by the Farriers when they ſhooe horſes; boyl theſe both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60082:4"/>
in half lye and half water, and ſo put thy ſhirt into it, and afterwards dry it in the Air, without waſhing it out any other way, and not a lowſe will come into it. This Experiment is found approved amongſt the old <hi>German</hi> Souldiers; and although there ſhould be a lowſe in thy ſhirt, it would not ſtay there.</p>
               <p>If thy feet be moiſt and ſweaty, (which is very troubleſome not only to thy ſelf, but to others alſo,) take the filings of Braſs, which are ſometimes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for duſt to dry moiſt writings with, and put ſome of it into thy ſocks, and walk upon it. Refreſh this every other or third day, and thou ſhalt ſoon be freed of that inconvenience: Nor be thou troubled, that it makes, as it will do, thy feet look greeniſh; for there is no hurt at all in that, ſince you are not like to put them in your cap.</p>
               <p>Take alſo with thee ſome Stags or Bucks-greaſe, to make uſe of in caſe thou ſhouldſt be galled any where in riding, or going on foot. Anoint the part therewith at the fire-ſide, and it will ſoon be healed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60082:5"/>To prevent Ruſt, draw thy Sword through the fat of a Gooſe or Capon, or greaſe thy Arms therewith.</p>
               <p>Take care to have always about thee a hard cruſt of Rye-bread; for if thou art dry, and deſtitute of water, wine or beer, to quench thy thirſt, chew ſome of this dry cruſt, and it will moiſten thy mouth, and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abate thy thirſt. The ſame may be done with a Leaden-bullet, rolled to and fro in the mouth, Lead being cooling.</p>
               <p>It hath been preſcribed above, to take with thee the Herbs <hi>Imperatoria</hi> and <hi>Carlina.</hi> Of this be mindful; for if it ſhould happen, that thou ſhouldſt be obliged to ſtand ſome hours in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail or in the field, take a piece of it in thy mouth for hunger, thirſt, and refreſhment, and thou ſhalt find, it will keep thee a good while from faintneſs. But woe to thy fellows, if they want it; for they will certainly faint, unleſs thou be ſo kind as to give them a ſhare in thy proviſion.</p>
               <p>In the beſt Apothecary-ſhops may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60082:5"/>
be found a root, called <hi>Coſtus,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like Cinnamon; which hath the ſame effect. And if others ſhould eat Onions, others drink Brandy, and I only hold in my mouth of this root the bigneſs of half a pea; I ſhould keep in breath a good while longer than they. But take notice, that this, I ſpeak of, is not the common <hi>Coſtus,</hi> which hitherto hath been ſold for the true in common ſhops; but that which comes to us from the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou art a Horſe-man, take a good quantity of Bay-ſalt, a little Brimſtone, Clove, and Ginger, and mingle with it ſome of the powder of the two above-ſaid herbs, <hi>Imperatoria</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina,</hi> and give it to thy Horſe, or in caſe of want of Provender let him have of it upon his bitt, or give him ſome upon a ſlice of bread, and it will make him ſtrong and vigorous.</p>
               <p>If thou art to ride in a <hi>German</hi> Saddle, the two hind-knobs whereof are wont only to be ſtuffed out with ſtraw or horſe-hair; get thee made two Tin-flaskes with good ſcrews, fitted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60082:6"/>
for thoſe places. In one of them carry Brandy, in the other Vinegar. The Brandy will ſerve thee in cold nights, and freſh mornings; and 'twill be good alſo for thy horſe, giving him a little of it upon bread. The Vinegar will be of uſe to thee for the heat of the day, waſhing thy mouth with it, as alſo ſpirting a little of it into thy horſes mouth. Beſides, mingling it with water, it will afford thee a good cooling drink.</p>
               <p>If it be very cold, put ſome of that horſe-hair, that is wont to be curried out of their mains and tails, into thy boots. I never received on ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions more warmth from any thing, eſpecially keeping my ſelf dry. A Hares-skin is alſo good for this purpoſe, making ſocks of it; but if it grow wet, 'tis naught.</p>
               <p>Gather of the Wheel-greaſe that runs out at the nave of the Wheels, and would elſe be loſt, which hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſome of the ſubſtance of the Iron that is about the Axel-tree, witneſs its blackneſs: This is a good Ointment for Horſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60082:6"/>When thou comeſt into the field, and art to lye abroad, look out for ſome riſing ground, that the Rain, which may poſſibly fall, may run away from thee: And avoid as much as is poſſible, Vallies, Mariſhes, Ditches, Meadows, and the like low and moiſt places.</p>
               <p>Beſides, obſerve the <hi>Air,</hi> and put up thy Tent towards the Eaſt; which quarter though it be cool, yet 'tis wholſom. But leſt it ſhould be too cool, order it ſo, that thou mayſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that wind, which comes from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Eaſt and South, as being one of the wholſomeſt of all Airs, and temperate, the South-air qualifying the ſharpneſs of the Eaſtern. Beware of the Weſtern Wind, eſpecially that which blows from between the South and Weſt. The Air of Mid-night is wholeſome enough and dry, but ſharp and piercing. Believe it, a Souldier is much concern'd in the Air; nor hath <hi>Hippocrates</hi> without cauſe written a whole Book <hi>De Aere, Aquis &amp; Locis,</hi> to teach, how the Air, Water, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60082:7"/>
Places are to be diſcerned and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</p>
               <p>Moreover, look about thee for good cleer <hi>Water,</hi> ſuch as grows warm and cool again ſooner than other waters; and obſerve this mark for my ſake. I know water, that will not boyl Peaſe, Vetches, Stock-fiſh, Flounders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In ſome Springs Iron is turn'd into Braſs, and great care is to be had in the choice of water for drinking.</p>
               <p>But if thou canſt not have Spring-water, but art neceſſitated to uſe Pit or Ditch-water; have a care not to drink it without ſtraining, leaſt thou ſhouldſt ſwallow Frog or Snake-ſpawn. For I have known and had in my cure a Countrey-man, who voided, though not at once but at different times, two hundred fifty and five Frogs, and of them many in my own houſe, in the preſence of divers Eccleſiaſtical and Secular Perſons; and ſome of the biggeſt of them, being dryed, are ſtill to be ſeen in the Repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory of <hi>Mantua,</hi> as alſo in that of Mr. <hi>Philip Hainhofer</hi> at <hi>Auſpurg.</hi> And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60082:7"/>
there is a Cook in the Hoſpital of <hi>Weſſenburg</hi> or <hi>Landsberg,</hi> who, (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by the event) had drunk the Spawn of Serpents, out of which were bred divers Serpents in his body, ſome of which he voided by virtue of the Medicine he took, amongſt which there was one of the length of a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian</hi> Ell. The Man hath been ſince in good health, and continues in his ſervice to this day.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it will behoove you to ſpread your handkerchief over the Ditch-water, and ſo drink through it; or if you take any of it up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, quench firſt a red-hot Stone or Iron in it, whereby the noxious quality will be deſtroyed. Or, if you lye ſtill, and can get any Oyl of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, let ſome drops of that fall into it, and you need not then fear any corruption or poyſon in ſuch water. Otherwiſe, if time will permit, let it boil up and cool again, and put a cruſt of bread into it, and you may drink of it ſafely.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Waters that run out of ſtony
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60082:8"/>
hills and from under rocks, are the beſt; to which may be reckon'd thoſe Springs, that flow from high places, and purge themſelves in clear ſand and pebles.</p>
               <p>If thou meet with Beer or Wine, take heed of exceſs; and forbear drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king New beer that hath not yet done working, or is not ſome days old, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe new beer cauſeth the <hi>Strangury.</hi> And in caſe <hi>this</hi> ſhould trouble thee, take a handful of Hay-bloſſoms, boyl them in water, and Urine over it, drawing into thy body the warm ſteam thereof, and anointing thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel ſeveral times with warm ſuet.</p>
               <p>If thou art hot, and canſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear drinking, make water firſt; then waſh thy mouth, and cool the arteries on both thy temples, and thoſe of both thy wriſts; and then drinking will hurt thee leſs.</p>
               <p>If you chance to drink whilſt you are hot, (which is ſo dangerous a thing, that ſome have dyed within 24 hours after it; others have fallen into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Coughs, others been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60082:8"/>
with Pains in their ſides and with Impoſtumes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) then take of the leaves of <hi>Bellis</hi> or <hi>Daiſy,</hi> which grows in all meadows and paſture-grounds, and is green both winter and ſummer, and waſh them clean, and dreſs them like a Salad with Oyl, Vinegar and a little Salt, and forthwith eat thereof; and it helps immediately, as I know by much Experience. But this muſt be uſed preſently, the ſooner the better. I can ſay with truth, that in all my Practice of Phyſick for above 20 years I have not met with any Experiment of ſo quick an Operation from any herb, as from this. But here I muſt note, that I have always uſed the <hi>Red Daiſy,</hi> and have not tryed the other ſorts; though I am apt to believe, the others may have the like effect. You muſt not eat the Flowers, but only the Leaves. This Experiment ſhould be put up on all poſts every where, for the good of Courriers, Mowers, and other labouring Men, that are wont to drink plentifully when they are hot, and thereby ſpoil themſelves in great numbers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60082:9"/>But to proceed; as thou art to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of exceſs of drinking at all times, ſo thou art eſpecially to forbear when thou art to ſtand Sentinel, leſt thou ſhouldſt fall a ſleep; whereby thou mayſt loſe thy life, at leaſt, thy place and thy preferment for ever.</p>
               <p>Neither be fond of Gaming at dice, tables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whence are occaſioned quarrels, miſtruſts, deceit, ſwearing, and what not?</p>
               <p>Avoid alſo the company of baſe women, leſt thou ſhouldſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to undergo the Mercurial Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livation, and with it a very lean Diet, of thin broth, water-gruel, barley-broth, prunes, roaſted apples, and ſuch like, without any fleſh-meat at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Concerning the Phyſicians and Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions in an Army.</head>
               <p>EVery Army ought to be well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with one or more able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60082:9"/>
ſuch as are not only expert in the cure of inward Diſeaſes, but alſo underſtanding in outward Caſes, as Wounds, Burnings, Luxations, Diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, <hi>Eryſipelas's</hi> or St. <hi>Antony</hi>'s Fires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Phyſicians ought to be no Youngſters, that are lately come from Schools and Univerſities, knowing only in Controverſies and Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſuch as are expert in the Cure of Diſeaſes, eſpecially ſuch as are moſt frequent in Armies. They are alſo to be Men of good nature, great honeſty and condeſcenſion, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take pains with the poor as well as the rich. Phyſicians thus qualified may ſo gain the hearts of the Souldiers, that theſe will love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them as if they were their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the Chirurgions ought to be learn'd, diſcreet, and affable, ſuch as have been long vers'd, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd, in all the operations of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, that can diſtinguiſh well of Diſeaſes, and with prudence make
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60082:10"/>
their judgments thereon: They ought alſo to be diligent, and careful of thoſe committed to their charge, and very knowing in all manner of outward applications, as Unguents, Plaſters, Pulments, Lenitives, Stiptiques, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractives, Digeſtives, Cauſticks, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charotiques, as alſo their Mollifying, Diſſipating, Repelling, Suppura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Mundifying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines. They ought to be skilful in diſcerning them, and withal in knowing well the caſes and times where and when to uſe them. They are to be very careful in obſerving the beginning, middle and end of Ulcers, Wounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince it often may be impertinent and even hurtful too, to uſe that in the beginning, that may be pertinent and beneficial in the midſt of the cure, and the like.</p>
               <p>An able and dextrous Chirurgion is a great Treaſure in an Army, and cannot be enough valued, eſpecially if he conſult in all dangerous caſes with an underſtanding Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>Theſe two, Phyſitians and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60082:10"/>
are to be intimate friends to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, aſſiſting one another without envy and pride, for the better relief and the greater ſafety of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients.</p>
               <p>'Tis very neceſſary, both theſe ſhould go abroad and travel before they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to practiſe, thereby to acquire experience, and to learn alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the more diſcretion and gentleneſs with all ſorts of humors. And when they come to practiſe, the Chirurgions ought to adviſe with Phyſitians, who are but lame Doctors, if they be not skilled in Chirurgery; ſince this is the third part of Phyſick, from which it can and ought not to be ſeparated, being an integral part thereof. It is recorded in hiſtory, that above 2000 years ſince, <hi>Podalyrius</hi> and <hi>Machaon,</hi> Sons to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> went both with <hi>Agamemnon</hi> in the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for <hi>Troja,</hi> and there purchaſed great honour by their practiſe not ſo much of Phyſick as Chirurgery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60082:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Fevers, Hungarian Diſtempers, Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Fevers, and other Peſtilential Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, as alſo of Hereditary Maladies, together with their Remedies.</head>
               <p>'TIs known ſeldom to fail, that in an Army there reigneth ſome Diſeaſe or other, according to the nature and conſtitution of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Air, and Diet. The reaſons are;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> that amongſt ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men, raiſed from ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent places, there are to be found Men of very different tempers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ſound and unſound; and amongſt the latter, ſome that are ſcabby, others ſcorbutical, others la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under venereal Diſeaſes, many inclined to dangerous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious Fevers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian muſt have a watchful eye upon, and endeavour to prevent their ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60082:11"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that Souldiers in an Army want conveniences wherewith to take due care of their health; but are often conſtrain'd to expoſe themſelves and ſleep in the open Air on moiſt ground, the vapours whereof penetrate into their bodies; and they are careleſs or want opportunities of expelling them out again by ſweat. Whence is cauſed an inward putrefaction in the blood and humors, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proceeds ſo far, as to aſſume a venomous nature, and to break out into ſpots, tumors, bubo's, carbuncles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that Souldiers commonly keep an irregular diet. Sometimes they have plenty and do ſuper-abound; at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times they have nothing; and then being very hungry, when they come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to a place of plenty, they over-feed and ſurfet; whence are bred cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in the ſtomach, and corruption, which cauſeth malignant Fevers in abundance. Beſides, they often feed upon meat that is unwholeſome, as ſtinking Veniſon, rotten cheeſe, muſty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60082:12"/>
bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which cannot but occaſion many Diſeaſes. And when they come to places, where Fruit abounds, as Apples, Pears, Plums, Melons, Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Grapes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they over-eat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and thereby cauſe Gripings in the Guts, <hi>Diarrhaea's, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> ſometimes the Air is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, eſpecially after a great battel, and ſlaughter of Men that remain unburied; whereby the Air being tainted infects the living that take it in. Which is often made worſe by the exhalations of low and mooriſh ground, and by thick fogs.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the general Cauſes of the common Diſtempers reigning in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; againſt which thou art to arm thy ſelf accordingly. Firſt then be careful in thy Diet; eat not greedily and indiſcreetly every thing that comes to hand; and though it be good, yet eat and drink not too plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully of it, but reſtrain thy appetite, conſidering how deſtructive every ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs may be to thy health.</p>
               <p>If thou canſt and haſt no averſion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60082:12"/>
from it, drink every morning of thy own <hi>Urine,</hi> which prevents corruption in the Stomach, opens obſtructions in the Liver, Spleen, Meſaraic Veins; which if not removed, there will follow Fevers, the yellow Jaundice, Swellings, and Difficulty of breathing. If thou art averſe from doing ſo, eat ſome bread and butter with rue on it; or, if it be not hot weather, take in the morning the quantity of a haſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut of Mithridate or Treacle; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe in brandy, or rather in Spirit of <hi>Juniper-berries,</hi> ſome <hi>Zedoary, Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica,</hi> and a little <hi>Citron-peels,</hi> and drink a ſpoonful of it in the morning.</p>
               <p>When the Air is corrupted, and there be at hand a Goat, rub thy ſelf at him, and let not the ſtrong ſmell keep thee from it. Alſo put Quickſilver in an empty haſel-nut, cloſed up with <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wax, and hang it about thy neck; or the <hi>Zenechton</hi> prepared of <hi>Arſenic,</hi> (after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by and by to be deſcribed,) ſowed up in thin leather; for if it ſhould touch the bare skin, it would cauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60082:13"/>
bliſters and do harm. This <hi>Zenech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> is a plaiſter, out of which are cut pieces of the bigneſs of a dollar, which are carried about the neck, and hang down near the heart; keeping good a whole year. And when the infection is paſt, this <hi>Zenechton,</hi> being reduced to powder, will yet ſerve to kill rats and mice with. It is to be thus prepar'd;</p>
               <p>Take of yellow and white Arſenic, of each an ounce, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>/4 of an ounce; of <hi>gummi Tragacanth</hi> ½ an ounce; put this <hi>gummi</hi> in Roſe-water or in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water over night, and it will yield a ſlimy water. Then beat thy Arſenic in a mortar, and put ſo much of this gummed water to it, as is neceſſary to reduce it to a paſte having the conſiſtence of dough; work it well and round it, and then cut off a ſlice of the bigneſs of a dollar, ſomewhat thicker; let this ſlice dry in the Air, and ſow it in a piece of thin leather (well-dreſſed dog-skin is the beſt for this purpoſe;) carry this about thy neck ſo as to let it hang down
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60082:13"/>
upon, and to touch the place of, thy heart. Some mix with it a proportion of the powder of dried toads, which I have done my ſelf, it being eſteem'd more powerful. Some carry about their necks dried ſpiders; <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> commends <hi>Celondine,</hi> leaves and root, carried about the neck.</p>
               <p>Remember alſo to burn frequently <hi>Juniper-wood</hi> before thy tent; though all ordinary fires cleanſe the Air; Upon which account <hi>Hippocrates</hi> adviſed great fires to be made in <hi>Greece</hi> at the time of a great plague, which was thought to have been remov'd by that means. Some burn only a few chips of Juniper-roots, or ſome of the berries of that ſhrub, which is as effectual.</p>
               <p>If theſe means cannot be had, burn ſome Gunpowder, ordering it like a train; this purifieth the Air likewiſe. And the volleys of ſhot made mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and evenings in a camp, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce very much to the diſpelling of miſt, and qualifying raw weather.</p>
               <p>Frankincenſe alſo, Maſtick, and ſuch other perfumes as dry and clear
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60082:14"/>
the Air, may be very uſefully burnt; and even a Scholars perfume made of waſte <hi>Paper</hi> is not to be deſpiſed.</p>
               <p>If thou canſt get <hi>Rue,</hi> ſmell often to it: And remember me for this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral hint, to take good notice of all herbs that are green winter and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and which are not eaten by Horſes or Cattel; for they are endow'd with excellent virtues for the good of <hi>Man,</hi> and therefore made to grow at all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the year.</p>
               <p>When the Air is peſtilential or breeding any Epidemical Diſeaſe, then waſh thy face with Vinegar every morning. If thou canſt get <hi>Acetum</hi> of Rue, Elder-flowers, Lavender, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Marigold-flowers, 'tis the better. Or, if you have the conveniency, prepare the following <hi>Acetum:</hi> Take Rue, Elder-flowers, Burnet-roots, white Dittany, Carlina, of each equal quantity; a few Orenge or Citron-peels, (of which the latter are the better of the two,) and a little Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, and ſome Walnut-kernels (the freſher the better,) leaving the bitter
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60082:14"/>
skins upon them; put all theſe into common Vinegar, and with this infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion moiſten every morning thy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, mouth and noſtrils, and the beating arteries of both thy wriſts; taking down a good ſpoonful of it, and thou haſt a good preſervative.</p>
               <p>If it be cold weather, take Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica-roots, Zedoaria, white Dittany, ſome dried Citron-peels, and a little Camphir, infuſe them all in Brandy, eſpecially in ſuch as is made out of Wormwood or Juniper-berries. Of this liquor drink in the morning a ſpoonful. But if thou be of a hot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, then content thy ſelf with the former <hi>Acetum,</hi> in which you may mix a little Treacle.</p>
               <p>Some adviſe to take faſting ſome of the Juyce of Marigold, freſhly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd out of the flower and leaves, as a good preſervative againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. This I have not tried; but I have often in ſuch caſes uſed the <hi>Acetum</hi> of Marigold-flowers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for a cordial and ſudoriſick, and, I think, with very good ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60082:15"/>Or make an Electuary, of Rue and Juniper-berries, of each equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, adding thereto a double quantity of Walnuts, with their bitter skin on them, ſome Figs, a little Treacle, and a little Saffron; beat them together in a mortar, and pour on them, whilſt thou art beating, as much Rue-vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar as will reduce it to a thick Puls or Electuary: Of this take the bigneſs of a haſel-nut or two, faſting.</p>
               <p>Take the roots of the greater <hi>Burr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Celondine,</hi> both well cleared, and the bark of Aſh; infuſe them 24 hours in half White-wine and half Rue-vinegar; then diſtill it, and in the diſtilled water mix a little Brimſtone-oyl, to render it a little ſowriſh. Of this take two ſpoonfuls in the morning for a preſervative. But if any be already infected with the Plague, let him take of the ſame ſix or eight ſpoonfuls at a time, and ſweat upon it, it being a very ſudorifique li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, which, under the name of <hi>Aqua Bardana compoſita,</hi> hath been uſed by me and my Collegues in Hoſpitals and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60082:15"/>
other places with very great ſucceſs. You may mix ſome Mithridate with it, if you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>Elſe take <hi>Carlina, Imperatoria, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaria, Valerian, Saxifrage, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, Gentian, Angelica</hi> and <hi>Zedoaria,</hi> all cut ſmall; infuſe them in Brandy, and drink of it a ſpoonful in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for a preſervative; but if thou haſt the contagion, take <hi>two</hi> ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, to ſweat upon it, in caſe the peſtilential poyſon be not yet broken out, and the Patients tongue not dry; but if it be, content thy ſelf with the newly preſcribed <hi>Acetum,</hi> as being more ſafe, and an inflammation being to be feared from the Brandy.</p>
               <p>Hold <hi>Zedoar, Angelica, Lovage,</hi> or <hi>Imperatoria,</hi> in thy mouth; but if thou be ſubject to the Head-ach, then cut it firſt ſmall, and infuſe it in Vinegar, and let it ſtand infuſed for the ſpace of 24 hours; then take it out again, dry it, and uſe it as preſcribed above.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the good <hi>Preſervatives</hi> reckon this alſo: Take <hi>Garden-rue,</hi> beat it in a mortar, pour Vinegar on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60082:16"/>
it, and ſtrain all through a cloth; mix ſome Treacle with it, ſet it by in a glaſs, and take of it in the morning half a ſpoonful or a whole. Put a little Camphir to it, if you will have it ſtronger.</p>
               <p>Or put Camphir in Wormwood-wine, and drink a good draught of it every morning.</p>
               <p>When I ſerved in times of great mortality, I infuſed in Wine <hi>Carduus benedictus, Wormwood, Scordium, Dictamne</hi> of <hi>Creet, Burnet-roots,</hi> and <hi>Citron-peels,</hi> and after I had taken every morning a good meſs of ſowriſh broth, I drank after it a good glaſs of this infuſion. As long as the herbs retain a bitterneſs, freſh wine may be infuſed upon them.</p>
               <p>Infuſe alſo white and well cleanſed <hi>Garlick</hi> in <hi>Acetum</hi> made of Rue, and take of it a ſpoonful or two in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>In the Apothecary-ſhops are Pills, call'd <hi>Peſtilential Pills:</hi> Among theſe cauſe a little Camphir to be mixt, and of it let Pills be made; of which take at once three or four every week,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60082:16"/>
taking them in a ſpoonful of White-wine, an hour before ſupper. Theſe prevent all inward putrefaction, and keep off all infection, nor do they ſuffer any collection of morbifique matter within thee, though they purge not, but only keep the body ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble. They are made up of Aloe, Myrrhe and Saffron. Formerly I have printed a whole Book of ſuch Pills, which I call'd <hi>Marocoſtinas</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> where I have deſcribed their vertues at large.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Rich</hi> may ſerve what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows: Take <hi>Terra<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sigillata, Bolus Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus, Pulvis Alexipharmacus,</hi> or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoardicum Nicolai,</hi> or the <hi>Cordiales A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrini Benedicti;</hi> item <hi>Species de Hydcintho, Aqua Stapediana, Acetum Theriacale,</hi> or the <hi>Red Hungarian Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> all theſe ſerving not only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, but alſo to recover, by Gods bleſſing.</p>
               <p>Provide out of the Apothecaries-ſhops Paſtils of the extract of <hi>Angelica</hi> or <hi>Zedoaria;</hi> take one or two of them in thy mouth every morning, and there let them melt down.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60082:17"/>Keep thy body clean every way; be chearful; avoid raſhneſs; nor be affraid, conſidering that many have been infected by fear, terrour, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy. Chear thy ſelf up now and then with a glaſs of good and ſincere Wine, but not to exceſs. <hi>Never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi> nor <hi>never full.</hi> One that is empty, will ſoon be caught with this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, eſpecially if he live amongſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected people. If he do, let him drink a good draught of Wormwood-wine, Juniper-berry-wine, Roſemary, Sage, or Zedoar-wine; which may keep thee from many dangers. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, not to drink more of it than will chear thee up and revive thy Spirits. At leaſt, drink a little Wine with Camphir and Vinegar, kindling the Camphir and letting it burn in the Wine, ſo as to let it ſink into it; for if it burn on the top, it will there remain ſwimming: And if the Wine be skinned over with it, kindle it again till it be quite burnt out. Take of Camphir for one draught, the quantity of a peaſe; but if thou be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60082:17"/>
ſubject to the Head-ach, then Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir will not agree with thee.</p>
               <p>In caſe that any come to be infected, he is forthwith to be ſeparated from the ſound, and to be laid to bed, ſo as his head and ſhoulders may lye ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what high; by which means he will be leſs ſubject to faintneſs. Then let him preſently take ſome ſudorifick Medicine, to make him ſweat; for if the poyſon be not ſpeedily driven from the heart, the Patient is loſt. You are alſo to take great care, that this Diſtemper prevail not, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcover it before the Patient be quite diſabled: For, as ſoon as any begins to droop, grows melancholy, faint and feeble in his limbs, ſo as that he is hardly able to hold up his head, drawing his breath with difficulty, letting his head fall to and fro, loſing his ſtomach, growing yellowiſh about his eyes, with the apples of his eyes ſtanding out, finding head-ach, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted heats and colds; as ſoon, <hi>I ſay,</hi> as theſe ſymptoms appear in times of the Plague, Spotted Feavers, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60082:18"/>
Diſeaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you may then look to it by times; foraſmuch as ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, that are already infected, go often about until the ſixth or eighth day, as I have known my ſelf, until the lurking poyſon of the heart has got the prevalency; and then the poor Patient is quite caſt down, and often dyes in very few days, and even in a few hours. Wherefore thou art not to ſtay, till the ſwellings and boils appear behind the ears, under the arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or till the Carbuncles, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo's, and the like, break out; but thou art immediately to make uſe of the beſt Medicines, thou canſt be Maſter of, to drive out the poyſon, if thou wilt ſave thy life. I never found any thing, that was conſiderable, done in the Plague, by means of Purging and Bleeding; but rather on the contrary, all thoſe that had Spots, if they were purged or let blood, ſoon after died. However, I will preſcribe nothing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially to any man; let every one endeavour to do, what he can give a good account of. I have, together
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60082:18"/>
with my Collegues, treated many hundreds in our Hoſpitals infected with the Plague, without ever open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a vein, and yet we have by Gods bleſſing recovered near 600 perſons; beſides thoſe that by the ſame mercy we have cured in their ſeveral Houſes.</p>
               <p>Now to procure ſweat in the very beginning, take the quantity of two haſel-nuts of Treacle, diſſolve it in common Vinegar; but if thou canſt have a cordial <hi>Acetum,</hi> made of Roſemary, Lavender, Elder-bloſſoms, Rue, Roſes, or Elder-berries, uſe it much rather, and give it the Patient to ſweat.</p>
               <p>Or take the roots of <hi>Celondine,</hi> boyl them in Vinegar, and diſſolve ſome Treacle in it: Or take <hi>Carduus bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus, Rue, Petaſites</hi> or <hi>Butter-burr,</hi> a little <hi>Angelica, Zedoaria,</hi> or <hi>Saxifrage-roots,</hi> boyl them together in half White-wine, and half Vinegar, or only Water, diſſolve a little Treacle or Mithridate in it, and let the Patient take it warm, to make him ſweat.</p>
               <p>Mithridate hath the like virtue with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60082:19"/>
Treacle, yet neither of them are ſafe to take for Women with Child, old Perſons and young Children.</p>
               <p>You may alſo make uſe to good purpoſe of the Saxon-powder, taking of it the weight of a Ducat in <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus benedictus, Scabius,</hi> or <hi>Sorrel-water;</hi> which Powder is thus to be prepared:</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Valerian</hi> half an ounce; <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>londine,</hi> or <hi>Nettel-roots,</hi> of each one ounce; <hi>Polypody, Althaea,</hi> (or <hi>March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallow,</hi>) wild <hi>Angelica,</hi> of each two ounces; of garden <hi>Angelica,</hi> four ounces; of the rind of <hi>Laurcola,</hi> (or <hi>Lowry,</hi>) an ounce and an half: Theſe roots are to be dug up in their beſt ſtrength, <hi>viz.</hi> between the middle of <hi>August</hi> and the middle of <hi>September,</hi> and being cleanſed, they are to be cut ſmall, and then put in a glazed pot, pouring a ſharp Vinegar upon it, ſo as to cover it two inches high. Then lute on the cover with a lute made of whites of Eggs and Flower; let all be boiled upon a gentle fire; then pour off the liquor, and dry the roots, and reduce them to powder, mixing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60082:19"/>
with it ſome 26 berries of <hi>Herbe Paris,</hi> (or <hi>One-Berrie</hi>) which look like Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-corns, very good againſt poiſon; and thus the powder is made. This herb grows in ſhadowed and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately moiſt places; I have found of it ſeveral times in <hi>Koſhinger-wood</hi> near <hi>Ingolſtad:</hi> It hath four leaves on one ſtalk, and one berry on the top. An herb belonging to the family of <hi>Solanum's</hi> or <hi>Night-ſhades;</hi> whence the leaves of it do very much cool Inflammations, eſpecially thoſe of the Eyes, when laid upon them.</p>
               <p>Take notice of <hi>Sorrel,</hi> bruiſe ſome of it and pour Vinegar on't, (the <hi>Rue-acetum</hi> is the beſt,) and ſtrain the juice through a cloth; put into it a little powder of <hi>Angelica,</hi> about the weight of half a Ducat; or of the root of <hi>Dictam,</hi> or of Butter-burr, or a little Treacle or Mithridate, and give it to ſweat.</p>
               <p>On this occaſion of mentioning <hi>Dictam,</hi> I muſt add, that in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey there grows only the white <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam,</hi> which is, among others, an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60082:20"/>
excellent Antidote, but you muſt take of it the double quantity and weight to that of <hi>Creta.</hi> You may boil of the root of half an ounce in half White-wine and half Vinegar, or, inſtead of the Wine, in <hi>Carduus-bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus</hi> water; and drink of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction warm, and put your ſelf to ſweat; or take of the powder of it a drachm and an half in warm broth, with a little Vinegar, for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dictam</hi> of <hi>Creta</hi> hath hairy leaves and purpureous bloſſoms, and is uſed in the preparation of Treacle. This herb by its odour drives away Serpents. The wild Goats being hurt by any Arrows eat this herb, and 'tis ſaid, that by this means the Arrows fall out of the wound. This perhaps hath no other ground than that of the Poet <hi>Virgil,</hi> affirming that <hi>Venus</hi> with this herb healed her Son <hi>Aeneas</hi> when wounded in the War. His words are <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 12.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60082:20"/>
                  <l>Hîc Venus indigno nati concuſſa dolore:</l>
                  <l>Dictamnum genitrix Cretaea carpit ab Ida,</l>
                  <l>Puberibus caulem foliis &amp; flore coman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</l>
                  <l>Purpureo, non illa feris incognita Capris</l>
                  <l>Gramina, cùm tergo volucres haesêre ſagittae.</l>
               </q>
               <p>About this time came in the Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Infection, which was a Diſeaſe that bred ſuch a putrefaction in the bodies of Men, that even when they were near death, they fell a vomiting, but that with ſuch a ſtench, that no body could endure it. Here thoſe Medicines do well, that preſerve the body from putrefaction; for the Plague, Spotted Feavers, and the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian Diſtemper, proceed all from inward corruption. And of them, the <hi>Plague</hi> attacks the Spirits reſiding in the Heart, and ſo killeth very quickly; whereas <hi>Spotted Feavers</hi> have their ſeat in the Blood, and therefore do laſt twelve, fourteen, and ſometimes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60082:21"/>
twenty days before they kill. But the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Diſeaſe is ſeated chiefly in the putrified Phlegm of the Head and Brains; whence thoſe that labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, are tormented with great and maniacal head-ach.</p>
               <p>But though theſe three Diſeaſes have their riſe from one and the ſame cauſe <hi>(Putrefaction,)</hi> and are to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſame remedies; yet is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in required the diſcretion of a prudent Phyſitian, for the ordering and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of Medicines according to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
               <p>Take a drachm of <hi>Zedoary,</hi> give it pulveriſed to the Patient in <hi>Acetum</hi> of Rue, or Elder, or Marigold-flowers, or even in common Vinegar: Let him ſweat upon it. 'Tis good againſt all ſorts of venom, and cauſeth a ſweet breath, as reſiſting inward corruption.</p>
               <p>In the Apothecary Shops you find an Electuary, called <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> found by that famous Phyſitian <hi>Hieronymus Fracaſtorius.</hi> It is like to Treacle and Mithridate; only 'tis red from ſome Ingredients giving it that colour.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60082:21"/>
This may be uſed with ſafety by Women with Child, young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and all ſorts of Perſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, as was ſaid above, Treacle and Mithridate may not. It is made chiefly of <hi>Scordium</hi> or <hi>Water-German<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> which hath the ſmell of Leek when bruiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> in his firſt Book <hi>De Antidotis, Chap.</hi> 12. writeth, that when in a great battel ſome ſlain bodies chanced to fall upon this Herb, they rotted not as far as they were touched by this Herb.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Fracaſtorius</hi> did compound this his <hi>Diaſcordium</hi> out of this Herb <hi>Scordium, Tormentil, Serpentaria, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, Bole Armeniac</hi> and <hi>Terra Sigillata,</hi> and ſuch like Ingredients.</p>
               <p>It is chiefly to be uſed in the hot Diſeaſes of the Head; which I have done many a hundred times. Take of it the weight of about two ducats in common Vinegar, or in Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, or rather in the expreſſed Juyce of freſh Sorrel, and ſweat upon it. Tis very good eſpecially in the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60082:22"/>
Sickneſs and other venomous and infectious Diſeaſes. To young People you may give a leſſer quantity, and proportionably you are to leſſen the doſe for Women with Child or in Child-bed, and little Children.</p>
               <p>Beſides take notice of the Powder of Doctor <hi>Heſſius,</hi> which hath been uſed with great benefit, and is thus prepared;</p>
               <p>Take a drachm of Sugar-candy, a quarter of an ounce of pulveriſed Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and a drachm of Camphir; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all to a fine powder; give of it to the infected Patient the weight of a drachm in Vinegar mingled with the water of Marigold-flowers, Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious or Sorrel, and ſweat upon it. If you have none of theſe waters, then look that the Vinegar be not too ſharp, and to that end dilute it with ſome wine and water. Mean time, though in this caſe I highly value Camphir, yet in ſtead of Ginger I would uſe Zedoary, Saxifrage, Carlina or Imperatoria, or the true <hi>Petaſites</hi> or Butter-burr.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60082:22"/>Again, <hi>Brimſtone</hi> is none of the meaneſt remedies in theſe infectious caſes; for it preſerves the body from putrefaction. Wherefore take of the noble Flowers of Sulphur a quarter of an ounce, being ſublimed from Colcothar; add to it one ſcruple of Camphir, an ounce of the Spirit or Oyl of Cyprian or Venetian Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. Put all this into a Glaſs-head, lute it well and put it upon hot ſand or aſhes, whereby the Oyl of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine will come to open the Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and produce a red colour like a Ruby, or at leaſt as yellow as a high-colour'd Hyacinth. Of this give ſome to the Patient three or four times, mingled with a little Treacle, or in Sorrel, Cardobenedictus, or Scabious-water. This Balſom is excellent alſo in ſore Breaſts that are growing puru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, taken in warm broth, or in a good wound-drink. But this muſt be in caſes of no great heat or inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which it would be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all the Remedies, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60082:23"/>
ſerve againſt Infectious Diſeaſes, that of <hi>Henricus Stapedius,</hi> to be found in my Book <hi>de Peſtilentia,</hi> is an excellent one, and perhaps the beſt for curing as well as preſerving; of which half a ſpoonful being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken faſting, is able to keep a Man well for twelve hours or more: But if any be already infected, he muſt take of it at any time imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, to the quantity of a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and an half, or two ſpoonfuls, for ſweating. Which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated every eighteen or twenty four hours, to make the Patient ſweat, till he recover, or till the Peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Boyls and Carbuncles break out behind the Ears, under the Arms, or elſe-where. This Water, though it be ſomewhat dear, yet its ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue countervailes its price. The older it grows, the more vertue it hath.</p>
               <p>Many have aſcribed great efficacy to the Blood of Animals: Thus old <hi>Democritus,</hi> (witneſs <hi>Galen,</hi>) prepared an Electuary of ſuch Blood, called
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60082:23"/>
                  <hi>Diathaematôn.</hi> Some eſteem much the Blood of <hi>Storks,</hi> becauſe they eat Toads and Snakes; others value the Blood of Hens, becauſe they eat Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and other venomous Infects. I ſhould eſteem moſt the Fleſh or Blood of Badgers; which is to be dried in the ſhade, and that done, you muſt mix with it Saffron, Camphir, and ſome or other of the Anti-peſtilential roots, as of Angelica, Zedoaria, or the like, together with a little live Brimſtone to the quantity of a ducat; which is to be taken in <hi>Acetum</hi> of Rue, or Marigold-flowers, or Walnuts, and in caſe of want of theſe, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Vinegar: Upon which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient is to ſweat. If thou art a good husband, have ready a good <hi>Acetum</hi> of Rue, Walnut-kernels and Marigold-flowers, taking the greater quantity of Rue; and as you uſe it, fill it up again with <hi>Acetum</hi> of Elder-berries.</p>
               <p>The Rich do uſe for their Phyſick in the time of the Plague the red Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian, as alſo the Imperial red and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60082:24"/>
gray Powder, Bezoar, Harts-horn, <hi>Antidotum Matthioli, Terra Sigillata, Bole Armeniack, Scorzonera</hi> and <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yerva, Species de Gemmis, Diamargariton de Hyacintho,</hi> and other high Medicines, of which I have largely diſcourſed in my above-cited Book <hi>De Peſtilentia.</hi> But I, though I have uſed ſuch reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies among the Rich, yet I content my ſelf commonly with the plainer and moſt common Medicines, of which I have more knowledge and experience.</p>
               <p>The Pickle of <hi>Ebulus</hi> or Walwort, (<hi>aliàs</hi> Dane-wort or Dwarf-elder,) which is of kin to Elder; as alſo the Pickle of Juniper-berries, are alſo of great uſe in this caſe.</p>
               <p>The Phyſitians of <hi>Ausburg</hi> made great uſe, in the year 1572, of the red Imperial powder; the compoſition of which is in the <hi>Auguſtan Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> at large, as alſo in my Book <hi>de Peſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſeveral means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſweat, which I eſteem to be of great efficacy for that purpoſe upon a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60082:24"/>
ſudden. And though Souldiers have not the conveniency of a bed for ſweating, when they are in a march, and often cannot put off their cloaths for many nights together; yet let them uſe ſuch ſudorifique means: for, though they cannot ſweat outright, yet they may fall into a dampiſh moiſture, which if it ſtrike not in again, may prove as good as a ſweat. Yet in this caſe he muſt turn his ſhirt: <hi>Quod non facit ſudor, praeſtat id tenuis udor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here is to be noted, that 'tis not enough, once only to give a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorifique Medicine to an infected Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; conſidering that the venom, like a raging Sea, is toſſed to and fro every way. And though it ſhould ſeem to thee, as if by thy approved Antidote thou hadſt overcome the Diſeaſe, the Symptoms of it excepted, yet thou art not to truſt in this caſe; for I my ſelf have been ſometimes deceived, and hard put to it to make good what by confidence I had omitted. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt not truſt to the <hi>once</hi> taking a ſudorifique potion or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60082:25"/>
becauſe ſuch malign and lurking Diſeaſes, that keep no ſtitch, do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed fly the firſt time from thy Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament, and hide themſelves under it, but they are wont ſuddenly to re-appear. Wherefore you muſt repeat the Antidotes, that were firſt admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to you, for the time of 16, 18, 20 or 24 hours, according to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and ſo long and often, till you judge your ſick Brothers or Friends Heart ſecured from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Venom.</p>
               <p>When the ſweating is over, thou muſt then refreſh thy Patient, firſt by drying him well, and next by giving him a little Vinegar to taſte in a ſpoon. The Rich may afford ſome ſlices of Citron, of which <hi>Theopompus Chius</hi> writeth, that the Tyrant <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archus Heracleota,</hi> who lived in <hi>Pontus,</hi> having poiſoned many People, the vertue of Citron was at length found out, of which a ſlice being eaten pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an effectual Antidote againſt it. The ſame vertue may be found in a ſlice of a common Apple; and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60082:25"/>
                  <hi>Syrupus de Pomis</hi> is one of the Cordials of our ſhops.</p>
               <p>But the thirſt, that uſes to follow upon ſweating, will not be quenched with ſo ſmall a matter; wherefore take three parts of water, one part of Vinegar, and, if the Patient be not too hot, one part of Wine, mixing ſome Sugar therewith, and of this let him drink a good draught, and it will cool and refreſh him.</p>
               <p>Beſides, take ſome of the guts of Hens, and ſome ſlices of Radiſh, ſprinkle them with Vinegar and Salt, and bind them to the ſoles of his feet; this will draw away the heat. But let not the Radiſh lye too long upon them, becauſe it will give a ſtink that may increaſe the head-ach, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the People that have the Plague are commonly troubled enough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out provoking it. Moreover you will do well to tye about his wriſts ſome Rue beaten with Vinegar. Anoint his Loyns and Back-bone with the Unguent of Roſes, or with freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but if there appear any Spots,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60082:26"/>
forbear to anoint him, leſt they ſhould be driven in.</p>
               <p>You will do well to have <hi>Epithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata</hi> of good things about you, as of Roſe-water and Elder-vinegar, to lay over the Heart; with which mix ſome Camphir. But if you find any thing of Specks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> broke out, you muſt uſe no wet thing.</p>
               <p>Anoint his Heart with Oyl of Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, take the Oyl of Sea-bloſſoms and of thoſe Earth-worms that appear after rain, of each ſix ounces, of St <hi>Johns</hi>-wort Oyl two ounces, of freſh Elder-bloſſoms and Rue, each a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and an half, of the <hi>Acetum</hi> of Marigold-flowers and Roſes, each a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three ounces, of live Spiders forty five: Boil all theſe together, till the Vinegar be ſo qualified, that when 'tis thrown into the fire, it cauſe no cracking there. Then ſtrain it, and in this ſtrained Oyl put a matter of five and twenty Spiders more, of the biggeſt ſort, and add to it of Camphir diſſolved in the Spirit of Roſes half a drachm; let it ſtand in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60082:26"/>
or upon hot embers for twelve hours, and then put to it of Treacle and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridate, of each half an ounce, and let them work together. With this Oyl anoint the eight Pulſes, <hi>viz.</hi> both Temples, behind both Ears, both Hands, and both Knees, as alſo the Heart. And this is an excellent <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaneum</hi> to Scorpion-oyl, much uſed by the <hi>Germans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, you muſt refreſh and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the Patient with convenient Meat and Drink; I mean with good Fleſh- or Barley-broath, with a little Vinegar in it to make it ſavoury to him who will have appetite too little elſe, till he have ſhaken off this veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Diſtemper; which when he hath done, his ſtomach will be ſo keen, that you will find work enough to keep him from ſurfetting.</p>
               <p>Be alſo careful to keep thy Patients Body open; if he be obſtructed, uſe a Cliſter, or take Butter or Hogs-greaſe, mixing a little Salt with it, or, if it be to be gotten, a little Mice-trickles, and put it into his bowels. Phyſick
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60082:27"/>
at the mouth for this purpoſe is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſafe: When the Patient is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the venom, a little liquor of ſtew'd Prunes with ſome Senna-leaves in it will do well for opening the body. Some freſh Butter eaten in the morning, or melted in warm Broath, and taken down, is wont alſo to keep the body ſoluble.</p>
               <p>The Drink of theſe Patients may be, Water with ſome Bread ſoaked in it; or take of ſuch Water, wherein Bread hath been ſoaked, one quart, and a little Vinegar, with two or three ſpoonfuls of Kitchin-ſugar, mingling it well together. If you have no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, uſe ſuch Water with Vinegar alone: This affords good Drink in malignant Feavers. Among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> it was drunk by the Souldiers, under the name of <hi>Poſca.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may alſo take a handful of well cleaned Plantain-roots, and boil them up in three quarts of Water, and then decant the Water, which though it be, ſomewhat bitter, yet 'tis very good in Fevers, and a good Drink in hot Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60082:27"/>If you have Oyl of Vitriol, let a few drops of it fall into clear Water, mingling it well; and you will have a factitious <hi>Sawer-brun</hi> or <hi>Acidulae.</hi> But uſe no Metalline Veſſel for this purpoſe. With this kind of Water many People have been ſerved in all ſorts of Fevers; the Oyl of Vitriol in ſuch Diſtempers, if rightly uſed, being very beneficial.</p>
               <p>But if a Man ſhould have with it any Pulmonick Diſeaſe, in that caſe he muſt forbear acid things, and uſe Liquorice, and content himſelf with Ptiſane. Nor is it at all good to uſe acids in Peſtilential Pleuriſies.</p>
               <p>And ſince on this occaſion we men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this caſe, and we having above given warning, not eaſily to blood in Peſtilential Diſeaſes; yet may Venae-ſection be ſometimes, upon good conſideration, uſed in that <hi>Pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie,</hi> provided it be done in the very beginning, and the Patient be ſtrong and full of blood. Yet this is not to leſſen the blood, but only to give it vent; but before bleeding the Patient
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60082:28"/>
is to ſweat by taking ſome of the above ſpecified Antidotes.</p>
               <p>If the Patient have violent Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, lay on his head Vine-leaves or freſh Cabbage-leaves; and, if you have no Alablaſter-ſalve, take two parts of Vinegar, and one part of Oyl of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives (the Sea-bloſſoms Oyl, and Elder-Vinegar were better;) dip long rags of linnen therein, and having well ſqueez'd them again, lay them luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm over the face and temples. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Vinegar alone is good. Of ſuch Applications you may make many, of <hi>Acetum</hi> of Roſes, Elder-bloſſoms, and the like, with a little Camphir. The expreſſed Milk of Peaches is alſo very effectual in this caſe.</p>
               <p>If at the going off of this Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a hot defluxion ſhould fall into the Eyes, take Camphir and infuſe it in water, and often moiſten the Eyes therewith; and if it ſhould be cold and windy weather, you will do well to keep your ſelf out of the open Air, and not to let this water dry up in your Eyes in the cold wind.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60082:28"/>In caſe of having loſt thy hearing, take of thy own Urine, and with it waſh thy Ears within, but withall dry them very well, becauſe that moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is very noxious to the Ears<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it often happens, that after the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian Sickneſs People grow deaf or hard of hearing. Others put the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Carduus-benedictus</hi> diſtilled with Wine into the Ears, or the Oyl of bitter Almonds.</p>
               <p>If thy Throat ſwell, or the Palate of thy Mouth be fallen down, garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize thy Throat with warm Milk, wherein Figgs have been boil'd, or ſweetned with Sugar. The Flowers of <hi>Phyllirea</hi> or <hi>Mock-privet,</hi> which grows in the hedges, boiled, and uſed for a gargariſm, heals alſo a ſore Throat. The ſame doth the middle rind of <hi>Oxyacantha</hi> or <hi>Haw-thorn</hi> if boiled, with a little Allom diſſolved in the Decoction. If you have the juyce of Mulberries, mix a little honey of Roſes with it, and often take a little thereof. The roots of Sloes boiled in red Wine, and the Mouth often
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60082:29"/>
waſhed therewith, is alſo very good.</p>
               <p>If thou haſt the Squinancy, boil Scabious in Meath, and drink thereof warm, when ſtrain'd. Beat Turnips and fry them in Butter or Oyl, and clap them in a cloth round about thy Neck.</p>
               <p>If thou caſt up blood, take Mouſe-ear, Ground-ivy, Cumfrey; boil them in half Wine and half Water, or in Meath, and drink often of it. But if the Plague reign not, open firſt a Vein.</p>
               <p>For a violent Cough, boil white Turnips, well cleanſed in common water; throw away this firſt water, pour on other water, and in it let the Turnips boil till they grow ſoft. Strain this water, ſweeten it with Sugar, or infuſe in it Liquorice cut ſmall; and drink of it mornings and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings warm. Or make a Decoction of <hi>St Johns bread,</hi> and drink it, abſtaining from all ſour and ſalt things,</p>
               <p>The bleeding at the Noſe is alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to perſons infected; which is no good ſign, though in ſound per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60082:29"/>
it often frees from the Head-ach, and cools the Liver. If this bleeding be too violent, clap Ice-cold water about the Patients Neck, or let him put his <hi>Pudenda</hi> in cold Vinegar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Inflammation of the Tongue, its riſe, and concomitants, together with the Remedies.</head>
               <p>VVHen the Tongue is infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the whole <hi>Oeſophagus</hi> or Weaſand is inflamed alſo, and this from beneath upward, becauſe the inward fire ſends up its ſmoak all along, as it were, that chimney, which like ſoot ſticks to it, drying and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame.</p>
               <p>But there is another Inflammation, much more dangerous, which taketh its riſe about the Heart, and therefore is call'd the Inflammation of the Heart, which proceeds from the great inflammation of the orifice of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60082:30"/>
ſituate near the Heart, in which is inſerted the ſixth pair of Nerves, which maketh the ſaid orifice very ſenſible of any pain. This part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeized by ſo great an inflammation, which is venomous withall, it muſt in a manner harden, and ſhrink; and this heat is of that extent, that, the inner Membrane of the Stomach and that of the Tongue being one and the ſame, what befalls the Stomach, the Tongue muſt needs be ſenſible of it. Whence it comes to paſs, that if the Gall overflows and paſſeth into the Stomach, the Tongue preſently finds the bitterneſs of it; or if the Stomach be full of ſlime, or foul, or the like, the Tongue is ſoon affected therewith.</p>
               <p>There is another kind of Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, by the <hi>Latins</hi> called <hi>Prunella alba.</hi> This is of the ſame kind with the reſt, but not of the ſame degree; for 'tis not of ſo dry a nature, as the others are, but commonly is moiſt, yet overlays all the Gums, the Throat, and the Weaſand with ſuch a tough white ſlime, like a kind of leather,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60082:30"/>
and ſo covers the Almonds with the ſame, that ſometimes it can hardly be removed even with Inſtruments, The Tongue is as if it were cruſted over with dough, the Gums like an Oven that by the heat of fire is burnt white, the Almonds cover'd as 'twere with white leather, and the Palate of the Mouth likewiſe. And in this caſe if the Patient will ſpeak, he lalls and ſtutters, his Tongue being burthen'd with a load of ſlime; or, if he make his Tongue wagg, the ſlime ſpins out like a thred, and ſo invades the Teeth as if they were laid over with varniſh. And when this varniſh on the Teeth grows black (as I have often obſerv'd it to do) and drieth on them, 'tis a mortal ſign; of which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quibus in febribus livores circum dentes naſcuntur, his fortes fiunt febres,</hi> 4. <hi>Aph.</hi> 53.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the three ſorts of Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; for which let us now ſeek out the Remedies, beginning from the laſt, the <hi>White.</hi> This is not to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd by gargariſms alone, but the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60082:31"/>
hand muſt be employed alſo. Take therefore Cotton-wool, or Flax, and wind it about a ſtick or rod, and dip this in Vinegar, and rake his Throat and Gums therewith, yet taking care not to make it raw; let him gargariſe between, and waſh well his Mouth with Water and Vinegar, or Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry-juyce. <hi>Privet</hi> that grows in the hedges, or the middle rind of <hi>Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn,</hi> boiled in Water and a little Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, then ſtrained, with a little Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armoniack put into it, is in this caſe an excellent gargariſm; but if there be bliſters upon the Tongue, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, then take inſtead of Sal-armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack a little un-burnt Allom, and mix it therewith. If you can have the Juyce of Turnips, or the Juyce of freſh Houſe-leek, diſſolve therein alſo a little Sal-armoniack, and uſe it to wet the ſtick, wherewith thou cleanſeſt the Throat of the Patient; dipping it often therein, and carrying it about the <hi>Uvula</hi> or Palate of the Mouth; and you will ſee lumps come away as big as Peaſe. The skin is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60082:31"/>
under this <hi>Prunella alba</hi> fair and red, but tender. Whilſt thou art clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Patients Mouth, let him often gargariſe with the Waters above-ſpecified, and he will clear his Mouth of the looſen'd lumps. If thou canſt get Mulberry-juyce mixt with Honey of Roſes, the Mouth will heal the better; for upon this ſort of Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation there uſually follows a Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Mouth; and in caſe thou perceiveſt any ſuch thing, take Wood-ſorrel, and the aboveſaid rind of Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn, make a Decoction of it, and put in it a little Allom, and often gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſe with it. Clean thy Teeth from the ſlime with Water well ſharpened with Vitriol.</p>
               <p>The common Inflammation of the Mouth may be cured with frequent waſhing of the Mouth, taking a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſm made of Houſe-leek, Lettice, Night-ſhade, or Self-heal Water, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little Honey of Roſes and Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry-juyce with it. Of this garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm the Patient is alſo to ſwallow a little, thereby to moiſten the Throat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60082:32"/>Some take Houſe-leek, and beat it, and put to a pound of it half an ounce of Sal-armoniack, mixing it well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And ſo they put it for ſome days in an earthen pot glaſed under ground; then they diſtill of it a Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>Balneo</hi> or in Sand: Which is excellent both to drink and to garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, though the Sal-armoniack make it a little unpleaſant.</p>
               <p>But there is nothing better to allay this Inflammation than Niter; which is ſo well known amongſt Souldiers, that they are wont to give one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gunpowder to drink, which Powder performs this effect not upon the account of the Coals or Brimſtone, but the Saltpeter.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe Experienced Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and Chirurgions endeavour to purifie Niter for this uſe, that it may have the greater effect; and this they do in manner following:</p>
               <p>They take of the pureſt Niter they can get, as much as they think fit; they beat it to a fine powder, and melt it in a large Crucible, and whilſt it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60082:32"/>
boils up and foameth, they pour into it a little powdered Sulphur, and ſo let it boil together, till the blew Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur-flame ceaſeth; then they caſt in more freſh Sulphur: Which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat often, and then pour out the Niter into an earthen veſſel glaſed, making Lozenges of it, of which they put one pulveriſed into a quart of limpid water, and ſo give the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to drink of it as much as he needs to quench his thirſt. Or they give of this purified Niter to their Patients, labouring under this Inflammation, the quantity of a ducat or half a ducat weight in Broath, or in Ptiſan, till they find the Tongue cleared of its ſlime.</p>
               <p>The uſe of Salt-peter thus prepared removeth alſo the Inflammation of the Heart, eſpecially if it be melted upon Lead, and then proceeded with as before. For Lead is a conſiderable cooler, of which cooling quality the Niter, whilſt it is melting upon it, taketh in not a little. Let then your Lead melt, and when 'tis melted,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60082:33"/>
diſſolve the Niter upon it, and then, to purifie it, caſt ſome Brimſtone into it, as was ſaid above, till it be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from all impurity; and then give of it to thy Patient two or three times a day, according as need ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, take live Crafiſhes and freſh Houſe-leek, beat them together in a mortar, ſqueeze out the Juyce, with it mix a little Sal-armoniack, or a pretty deal of thy prepared Niter; make a Potion of it, and give of it even cold to thy Patient, repeating this ſeveral times, every eight or ten hours once, according as you ſhall ſee occaſion.</p>
               <p>Or, take freſh Lard, (if it be ſalted, draw it through hot water to unſalt it,) and cut a ſlice of it two fingers large, and of the thickneſs of a knives back; put this into the Mouth of thy Patient, it is an excellent remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Inflammation; of which I ſhall give the reaſon hereafter. I have ſeen wonders done with it. But if thy Patient do rave, then faſten this ſlice of Lard with a thred and needle
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60082:33"/>
to his ſhirt or doublet, leſt he ſwallow it. Or take freſh Butter, and put it in cold water, and of it give thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient at a time the quantity of a haſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut to hold it upon his Tongue, and let it melt there; which will keep the Tongue always moiſt. And if thou work among this Butter ſome of thy prepared Niter, it hath a wonderful effect, though the taſte be not pleaſant.</p>
               <p>I promiſed above to explain the Reaſon of the Cure of theſe Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. When you take a garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm of the Waters of <hi>Night-ſhade, Wood-ſorrel, Knot-graſs, Endive, Houſe-leek,</hi> and the like, mingled with Vinegar, you do well, but this is not enough; the reaſon is: If you wet a piece of Leather, you make it indeed limber, but when it comes to be dry, it grows hard and ſhrinks; except you greaſe it over with ſome fatty matter, and then it will remain ſmooth. So it is with the Tongue; though it be made clean with garga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms, yet will it become again rough and untoward, unleſs ſome fatneſs be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60082:34"/>
uſed: For which cauſe I have directed to uſe Lard, or Butter mixt with Niter.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Almonds</hi> be ſwelled, thou muſt abſtain from all ſowr things, and prepare a gargariſm of Figgs, St. <hi>Johns</hi> Bread, Mallows-flowers, Liquorice, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-canes, mixing with it ſome Roſe-honey or Juyce of Walnuts, or the <hi>Rob Diamorom,</hi> gargling often with it, ſeeing that this ſymptom is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing; for when the Throat ſwells of it, few Patients do eſcape death, eſpecially if it be a Peſtilential Squinancy. And in caſe there appear any Tumour outwardly, take fine Flower, Milk and Saffron, making a Pulſe of it, and, to keep it from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, mix with it <hi>Althea-ſalve,</hi> or <hi>Houndstongue-ſalve,</hi> the Oyl of <hi>blew Violets, Mullein, white Lillies, Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile,</hi> or the like, adding a little Oyl of Scorpions to it, and applying this outwardly.</p>
               <p>Make alſo a Scraper of <hi>Alder-wood,</hi> if it may be had; if not, other wood will ſerve, though <hi>Alder</hi> be beſt. Throw it into cold water, and let it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60082:34"/>
lye there, uſing it as often as there is need; yet take heed of making thy Tongue ſore or raw.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Fevers, Belly-aches, Tumors of the Belly, Yellow Jaundiſe and Diſtempers of the Liver.</head>
               <p>IN Camps there is nothing more frequent than Fevers of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, ariſing from ill dyet, which Souldiers are often put to for want of better, eating what they can get, Cheeſe, Herbs, Fleſh half boiled, ſtale and muſty Bread and the like. Hence is gather'd a morbifick matter in the Stomack, which cauſeth putrefaction, and conſequently Stomack-feavers.</p>
               <p>In this caſe thou art firſt to purge: And for that purpoſe make uſe of the <hi>Pulvis ſolutivus de tribus,</hi> recommended above, taking the weight of a ducat or a ducat and an half, in warm broath, and faſting two or three hours after
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60082:35"/>
it. Or fetch from the Apothecary of the <hi>Tabulatum Diaturbith cum Rhubar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baro,</hi> or the <hi>Diaphoenicon in tabulis,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king half an ounce at a time, and keeping thy Chamber. Or, infuſe Sena-leaves in Wormwood-wine, and drink a ſmall glaſs-full of it an hour before thy break-faſt: This will alſo ſerve very well, eſpecially if ſome <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> have alſo been fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the Wormwood-wine.</p>
               <p>If thou art troubled with Gripings or Inflation of the Belly, take of Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doar, or Angelica-roots, or Orange-peels, cut them ſmall, and take at a time the weight of a ducat in hot broath. If the Inflation be much, take in the morning the quantity of a haſel-nut of Mithridate, faſting an hour after it; and if the pains of thy Belly prevail, make a Decoction of Wormwood in Wine, and drink of it as hot as thou canſt; this will allay the pains and give thee ſome ſtools. Mean time abſtain from raw Fruit, and Beer, Milk, Herbs; and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60082:35"/>If thou art ſwollen, take half a drachm of Rubarb, and about the ſame quantity or a little leſs of Mechocan; reduce it to powder, and take it in Wormwood-wine, or warm broath, in the morning faſting, and eat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within an hour or two after. Be careful to take down ſome Treacle in the morning faſting; but you are firſt to be purged. Otherwiſe make a Decoction of the Roots of Elecam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane and Pimpernel, or Swallow-wort, in Wine, and drink a warm draught of it mornings; it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Urine. If thou canſt bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it Wormwood, <hi>Carduus bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus,</hi> or Centory, add them in the Decoction, and it is a good potion for the Liver.</p>
               <p>An Herb, call'd by the <hi>Latins Eupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriam Avicennae,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> (I think) <hi>Common Hemp-Agrimony,</hi> hath a great operation in ſwelled People, drinking of the Decoction thereof, made in Wine. Beſides, uſe in this caſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley and Smallage-roots in thy meat. Boil Horſe-radiſh, and drink of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60082:36"/>
Decoction warm in the morning. Thy ordinary drink is to be a water, in which hath been boiled a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Cummin, Annis or Fennel. You may alſo now and then drink a little Wine, ſwelled People having no great heat in them.</p>
               <p>From theſe obſtructions of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Meſaraic Veins comes diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Breathing and a dry Cough, which occaſions the Inflation of the Belly, and helps to entertain the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and indigeſtions: Mean time there uſeth to follow upon this the Yellow Jaundiſe. For this, take the Roots of <hi>Cyclamen</hi> or Sow-bread, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to powder, and take the weight of half a ducat in Meath, or Wine mixt with a little Honey, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon it; and you ſhall find your ſheets diſcoloured of a yellowiſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. In the ſame manner make uſe of the Seed of <hi>Aquileja,</hi> or <hi>Columbine.</hi> I have reduced theſe three to powder, and mixt them together, and given of it the weight of a ducat to ſweat; which hath proved very ſucceſsful.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60082:36"/>
Orange-peels uſed in like manner, do alſo much good in this caſe. The bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Centory boiled in Meath, and a good draught drank of it warm in the morning, is alſo very good. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Decoction of the white Hore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound and Cichory-roots is alſo uſed to good purpoſe in this caſe. Theſe things expel alſo Worms, if any do lodge within thee; for which may alſo be uſed the Souldiers Pills of <hi>Aloe,</hi> called <hi>Marocoſtinae.</hi> In this caſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger of Squills is alſo an excellent remedy, taking of it in the morning early a ſpoonful, two or three, and exerciſing after it. It will open the Breaſt, and make you expectorate phlegm and ſlime in abundance.</p>
               <p>If you be troubled with Wind and Gripings of the Guts, be careful to have your Body ſoluble. Boil <hi>Calamus,</hi> cut ſmall, in broath, drink of it hot, putting a little <hi>Angelica,</hi> or <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort.</hi> Do this mornings and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and beware of drinking cold, and abſtain from all Milk, keeping your ſelf very warm, eſpecially about
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60082:37"/>
the Feet, which you will do well to bath with a Decoction made of Aſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabacca, Camomile, wild Trefoil, wild Marierom, wild Thyme, putting a little Salt into it. For your drink, boil Cummin, Annis or Fennel in water; and now and then a glaſs of wine may do well.</p>
               <p>Theſe Gripings may alſo be cured with drinking very bitter Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood-wine, as hot as you can endure it. This is alſo opening. If you boil Elecampane, and Orange-peels with the Wormwood, it will have the greater effect. And if you add to it <hi>Allium Sylveſtre</hi> (Crow-Garlick) you have an excellent Medicine for this purpoſe. This I have uſed my ſelf, and found preſent relief from it, when in a very hard Winter upon a Journey I was taken with theſe Gripings. 'Tis indeed a very unpleaſant potion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding bitter, eſpecially being to be drunk hot; but the good effects will make amends for that. If the pains ſhould not ceaſe after all this, mix with it the quantity of a haſel-nut of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60082:37"/>
Treacle or Mithridate, and ſo drink it off together.</p>
               <p>If you can get Malvaſy, mix a little Oyl of Olives with it, and drink of it warm. Oyl of ſweet Almonds would be better, one half of that and the other of Malvaſy; though theſe things perhaps will not ſo eaſily be had in a Camp. Freſh Butter may ſerve inſtead of Oyl.</p>
               <p>Elſe make a Decoction of Juniper-berries, or Laurel-berries, and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane in ſtrong Wine, and drink a good draught of it mornings and evenings. Or reduce the Herb <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus benedictus</hi> to powder, and drink its weight of a ducat in warm Malvaſy or other ſtrong Wine; it will remove the Gripings, eſpecially if you mix with it a little Zedoary pulveriſed.</p>
               <p>For your Meat, take Larks, if they chance to be in ſeaſon, draw them, and fill their bellies with Garlick, and ſo roſt and eat them.</p>
               <p>Make a Decoction of Burnet, or of Maſter-wort, and Laurel-berries, in Beer, ſtrain it, and melt a little
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60082:38"/>
Butter in it, adding a little Pepper, and ſo drink of it hot.</p>
               <p>For an outward Application, take the Oyl of Rue and Wormwood, dip Cotton into it, and put it warm to thy Navil. Or beat Onions, and fry them in Dill or Camomile-Oyl, wrap it up in a linnen Cloth, and apply it to thy Belly, where the pain is moſt violent, refreſhing it often.</p>
               <p>The Oyl of Laurel-berries, mixing a little Juniper-berry-oyl or Nutmeg-oyl with it, may be uſed with great benefit, anointing the Navil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and afterwards put to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil a warm dry bag filled with Bran and Camomile-bloſſoms. Or fry Cow-dung in the Oyl of Dill, or of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, or of white Lillies, and apply it thus to thy Navil, keeping thy ſelf, and eſpecially thy Leggs, very warm.</p>
               <p>If you perceive any Hydropical Diſtemper in you, make a Decoction of Wormwood and Juniper-berries in Wine, drink every morning a warm draught of it faſting. You may alſo to very good purpoſe boil with it Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-wort,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60082:38"/>
Burnet, or Succory roots, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo to it ſome Annis or Fennel-ſeed. But it will be requiſite firſt of all to purge with Mechoacan and Rhubarb; and now and then to repeat this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. Abſtain from Milk, Beer, Fruit, and all raw and obſtructing food. If you knew how to uſe Elder, you would have an excellent Purge to free your Body from the Hydropical water, becauſe the Juyce of the Roots of Elder purgeth Hydropical Perſons exceedingly: But 'tis not ſo ſafe to uſe it, unleſs you do it with great caution, becauſe a very little of it taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly purgeth both by ſtool and vomit, like Antimony. Half a nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhel full may ſuffice. The like effect you'l find in Elder-buds boiled, and then dreſſed with Oyl and Vineger like a Salad, eating a very little of it. But I adviſe you not to uſe too much of it; elſe it will caſt you into great faintneſs. The Juyce of the Roots of blew Lillies hath the like vertue, but is likewiſe to be uſed with great diſcretion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60082:39"/>Otherwiſe take Earth-worms, and having waſh'd them clean in Wine, reduce them to powder, and take of it for ſome mornings the weight of half a drachm in warm Broath or Wine, mixing a little Rhubarb with it.</p>
               <p>The Swelling of your Leggs may be removed by heating ſome Tiles and ſprinkling them with Wine, and clapping them about your Leggs to make them ſweat. For a ſwelled Groin, take warm Milk, wherein <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus Aromaticus</hi> hath been boiled, and ſweeten it well with Sugar, and apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of all ſorts of Fluxes; as alſo the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſmus,</hi> or vain endeavour of going to ſtool; and the Hemorrhoid or Riles, and <hi>Mariſca's</hi> or ſore Fundaments.</head>
               <p>IN Wars and Camps, Bloody and other Fluxes are very frequent, cauſed by an irregular and ill dyet;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60082:39"/>
and theſe Diſtempers, eſpecially the Bloody Flux, carry away abundance of Men. Where it is to be noted, that the Bloody Flux is infectious, and very catching.</p>
               <p>Common Fluxes and Looſeneſſes may eaſily be cured. Amongſt other Remedies, take burnt Harts-horn, and take it often in Broath; or pulveriſe Medlar-kernels, and take of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Broath likewiſe. Alſo an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary made of Quinces and Sloes will cure them. The ſame does Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and the Roots of Tormentil, Snakeweed, or the Roots of Cinque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foil, baked in Eggs, and eaten. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Seed of Dock, broad Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; item <hi>Terra Sigillata,</hi> or <hi>Bolus Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus,</hi> and Wheaten-bread coming hot out of the oven, and dipt in red Wine, and eaten. Again, Maſtick pulveriſed, and put into Almon-milk, red Wine, or Broath, the weight of a drachm, is good for ſuch a Looſeneſs eſpecially as comes from indigeſtion; adding a little Nutmeg or Galingal to it. Oaken-leaves alſo, or the Rinds
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60082:40"/>
of Pear-trees, with a little Mace boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Wine, and drunk, cureth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fluxes. Again, <hi>Burſa Paſtoris</hi> (Shepherds-Purſe) boiled in Steel-water with a little Coriander, and drunk, is alſo very good; and ſo are Crafiſhes boiled in Vinegar, and the ſcales beaten to powder, taking a drachm of it mornings and evenings, either in red Wine, or in Broath wherein red-hot Steel hath been ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times quenched. <hi>Hawes</hi> alſo boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and made into a thick Electuary, and ſtrained, is beneficial, if taken in the morning faſting, and an hour or ſo before ſupper, the quantity of a Walnut.</p>
               <p>Beſides, take new Milk with its Cream on it, quench therein divers times red-hot Pebble-ſtones, ſo that the Milk may grow hot of it; then mix with it two or three well-beaten Yolks of Eggs, two ounces of Sugar, melting in it an ounce and an halt of the Suet of a Deer or Stagg, and about half an ounce of <hi>Album-graecum,</hi> uſing it for a Clyſter, which cleanſeth and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60082:40"/>
healeth the Guts, and allays the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Blood and other corroſive humors, that annoy the Bowels.</p>
               <p>But take heed of not ſtopping too ſuddenly the Bloody Flux, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Laske; for if you do, the annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance will remain in the Body, and cauſe Impoſtumes, Difficulty of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and other dangerous Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. Wherefore conſult with thy ſtrength, and if that be conſiderable, make not too much haſt; yet keep a bridle upon it, ſo as to be able to ſtop it when there is need. Mean time, if it be without a Fever or heat, you may do much with new Milk, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it alſo mornings and evenings warm, ſome red-hot Stones having been quenched therein, and ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar mixed with it, to prevent curd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in your Stomach. This Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine was known to the famous <hi>Grecian</hi> Phyſitians, <hi>Aetius, Alexander Tral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus,</hi> and <hi>Galenus</hi> himſelf, <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>de Simpl. Med. facult.</hi> If you add a little <hi>Album-graecum</hi> to it, 'twill be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I have my ſelf done much good
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60082:41"/>
with thus prepared Milk, but then there muſt be no Fever; which if there be, you'l eaſily perceive it by a great thirſt, quick pulſe, hot hands, and little ſleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, Bloody Fluxes are not wont to be accompanied with ſhaking Fevers, but only with hot fits, which ſpend more of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients ſtrength in an hour, than ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Agues in ſeveral days; which is to be well heeded.</p>
               <p>Eggs boiled hard in Vineger, and given to the Patient, that is troubled either with the Bloody or any other Flux, it will be ſtopped.</p>
               <p>The Roots of Tormentil, or of Snake-weed pulveriſed, and this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der drunk in a convenient vehicle, the weight of a drachm, is one of the moſt approved remedies againſt theſe Flux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; Tormentil-roots being very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful not only to ſtop them, but alſo to take away their carching malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>The Moſs that grows on wild Roſe-ſhrubs, reduced to powder, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in Wine, wherein have been
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60082:41"/>
boiled the husks of Acorns; is an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved remedy in this caſe.</p>
               <p>Scrape red Lead or Rudle, ſuch as Carpenters mark their lines with, put it into Wine or Broath, wherein hath been boil'd the broader kind of Plantain and Tormentil-roots; or take it in an Egg.</p>
               <p>Hares-blood dried, and taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, is alſo a tried Medicine in this Diſtemper. <hi>Item,</hi> open a new-laid Egg, take out the white, and fill it up with Nutmeg, or the pulveriſed root of Tormentil or of Snake-weed, and give it the Patient to eat; or put into it ſome pulveriſed Blood-ſtone, and it will do good.</p>
               <p>I have uſed with good ſucceſs the Seed of the broader Plantain, groſly beaten, and roſted in an Egg, againſt the Flux; and I know it alſo to have been beneficially uſed againſt the Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Flux.</p>
               <p>Take of Mummy, a little Maſtic, Bol Armeniac, <hi>Sanguis Draconis,</hi> mix them together, and make a powder of them, and take of it in a convenient
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60082:42"/>
liquor, the weight of a drachm, once or twice a day.</p>
               <p>Take Rye-biſcuit, and boil it in water with Coriander and the roots of Tormentil or of Cranes-bill; quench ſome Steel in it once or twice, and give of it to the Patient to drink.</p>
               <p>Make a Decoction of Shepherds-purſe and Meadow-ſweet, in water and wine, and now and then drink of it.</p>
               <p>Burn live Craſiſhes in an earthen Pipkin well-cloſed, until they be ſo burnt as to be reduced to powder; of which give to the Patient mornings and evenings a thimble-full or two in a convenient liquor.</p>
               <p>A dried Liver of a ſucking Lamb, or of any other ſuch Animal, is very good in this caſe, provided ſuch a Liver, before 'tis dried, be boiled in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Let the Patient take a drachm of it twice a day. Alſo the Blood of a Lamb, or of a Hind, both dried, will have here a good effect.</p>
               <p>Take a Pigeon, Wood-cock, or Partridge, and having drawn any of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60082:42"/>
them, fill them with Maſtic and a little Nutmeg, and ſo roſt them on a ſpit, and whilſt they are roſting, baſte them with red wine, and ſo let them roſt till they grow ſo hard as will make them pulverable; then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them or any of them to powder, and take a ſpoonful of it at a time in warm broath.</p>
               <p>The higheſt Experiment in this caſe is <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> taken in the Juyce of the broader kind of Plantain, or in a Pulſe of red Beans, or Rice-broath; the doſe is half a dram. But when the pain is very great, you may then add to it ſome opiat Medicine, as of the <hi>Trochiſques de Garabe,</hi> or one onely grain of <hi>Laudanum Opiatum.</hi> And give the Patient now and then a little new-made Treacle, or mix with it a few grains of the <hi>Confection</hi> of <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes;</hi> for of ſuch Medicaments a Field-Apotheque is not wont to be deſtitute.</p>
               <p>For the Patients ordinary drink, boil water, and in it Coriander, dried Sloes, dried ſlices of Quinces, burnt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60082:43"/>
Hartshorn, Maſtic, Nutmeg, or any one of theſe; putting to it ſome of the roots of Snake-weed, Tormentil, or ſuch like adſtringent roots. Of this water the Patient may drink ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as his neceſſity ſhall require.</p>
               <p>The red Juyce of Quinces, boiled up without Sugar, is alſo much to be commended in this caſe, for ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening the bowels, two or three ſpoonfuls of it being taken at a time, and that twice a day.</p>
               <p>In many places a drink is made of Sloes, <hi>Piloſella</hi> or Mouſe-ear, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper-berries, infuſing them all in common water, and letting them fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment together. This yields a pleaſant acid drink, allaying the violence of the Flux, and quenching thirſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p>The Rich may make Granat or Quince-wine. But I have here un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to deliver ſuch things, as are parable and cheap for the poor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Souldier.</p>
               <p>I am ſorry, that in the Field there is no conveniency of adminiſtring
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60082:43"/>
Clyſters: For, though I preſcribe none without great neceſſity; yet Clyſters being of great benefit in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of the bowels; they being to them like Plaiſters, I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend in this Diſtemper Clyſters of Milk, wherein Pebble-ſtones have been ſeveral times quenched, mixing a little of the melted ſuet of a Stag or Hind, without any oyl or other fat. I remember, I had once a Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of quality, that had about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſtools within twenty four hours, who by the uſe of ſuch Clyſters, once or twice applied, was fully reſtored. The cauſe whereof is, that the Milk waſhes the bowels, and clears them of the ſharp humors that annoy them; moreover, it is healing and repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by reaſon of the Pebbles quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched therein. The Sugar is abſterſive, and helps to clean the injured places. The Far ſticks to the parts annoyed, to defend them from being further hurt by the ſubſequent humors, which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning down over it, can find no ſtay there, and conſequently cauſe no more hurt to thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:60082:44"/>Yet muſt you not put in any greaſie Fat, or any Oyl of Olives, becauſe they hinder healing; and all Oyl, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that of Linſeed, Poppies, Hemp and Almonds, is very ſharp; and you will find, that if any drop of Oyl of Olives ſhould chance to fall into your eye, no Juyce of Orenges or Limons is ſo ſtrong as to exceed the acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of that Oyl. But of this Oyl more will be ſaid in the next Chapter, to which I therefore refer you. If you would have your Clyſter yet mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and more ſanative, you may beat a yolk or two of new-laid Eggs, and mix them with it; though I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented my ſelf with the Ingredients before mention'd, and found great benefit thereby. Elſe you may in this caſe uſe for a Clyſter the <hi>Cremor hordei,</hi> mixt with yolks of Eggs beaten in it; which is alſo very good to waſh out the bowels.</p>
               <p>Here is no conveniency of making much uſe of Apothecary-ſhops; elſe many things might be preſcribed to lay upon the belly and the navil, as
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60082:44"/>
alſo divers fermentations, and ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical unguents. You may therefore content your ſelf with thoſe plain and eaſily parable means, already deliver'd, and be thankful to God for them.</p>
               <p>But then you are alſo to think upon means to obviate Symptoms of this Diſtemper, and particularly <hi>Drought,</hi> which is wont very much to torment people in this Diſeaſe. 'Tis true, Acid things do quench thirſt, but they cannot be uſed boldly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt uſe them with great diſcretion and warineſs. And as for ſweet things, they uſually increaſe thirſt, and do eaſily corrupt, and turn into gall. Wherefore give to the Patient preſerved Currans; or, if freſh ones be in ſeaſon, mix a quantity of them with Honey or Sugar, and give him of it to eat upon white-Bread and Butter. Or plump dried Black-cherries, or dried Damaſcene-prunes, in half Wine and half Water, and let him hold and ſqueeze them in his mouth. Or, if you can, mingle ſome Almond-milk with Chalybeat-water,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60082:45"/>
and let him drink thereof; and this is both meat and drink. Or let him drink water, wherein Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and roots of Tormentil have been boiled. Or boil in water dried ſlices of Quinces, roots of <hi>Biſtorta</hi> or Snake-weed, and burnt Harts-horn, put into it a toſted cruſt of Rye-bread rubb'd with Nutmeg, but let it not lye in it above a quarter of an hour, leſt the water ſhould thicken and become viſcous. Marmelat alſo of Quinces, Black-cherries, and Sloes, is proper in this caſe, giving the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient a ſlice of it to hold upon his tongue, and ſo to ſwallow it down.</p>
               <p>Further, you muſt learn how to remedy a <hi>Tenaſmus,</hi> which is more irkſome to the Patient, and occaſions more trouble to the Phyſitian, than the Bloody-flux it ſelf, ſince it night and day painfully provokes the poor Patient to go to ſtool, and yet to no purpoſe. For this I have uſed many remedies, but found almoſt nothing more beneficial, than Fomentations of this nature following: Take <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilla</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60082:45"/>
(wild Tanſie Silver-weed) Knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſs, Mullein, and Oak-leaves, of each as much as you pleaſe, put them into two linnen bags, and let them boil in Smiths-water, wherein much Iron hath been quenched: Squeeze out theſe bags between two boards, and let them be held alternately to the <hi>anus,</hi> as hot as can be endured. Black Pitch, ſuch as is found on Larch and Fir-trees, put upon a heated fire-ſhovel, and the fundament held over it, is alſo a good remedy; and ſo is Turpentine, uſed after the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>Again, take a black well-burnt Brick out of the hearth, heat it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly, and wet it with ſharp Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, and wrap it about with a linnen cloth, and let the Patient ſit on it as hot as he can endure it. This was the Experiment and Remedy of old <hi>Aetius;</hi> but he reduced the Brick to powder, and by boiling it in Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, reduced it to a pulſe, and ſo put it into a linnen rag, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied it to the fundament. You
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60082:46"/>
may chuſe which you pleaſe of the two.</p>
               <p>Milk-Clyſters, ſuch as above pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, would alſo be good, but that 'tis not ſafe with Clyſter-pipes to vex the <hi>anus,</hi> which is already ſore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Yet you may give a Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory of Deers-ſuet mixt with ſome Oyl of Mullein. And the grey <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompholox,</hi> or the white Camphire-unguent, or the like, mixt with it, would not be improper in this caſe.</p>
               <p>If there be a Falling down of the fundament, then let it often take in the fumes of the above-mention'd Herbs, adding to them the beaten ſtalks of Sloe-ſhrubs, and thoſe of red Roſes, as alſo Mouſe-ear, and Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort. The outer bark of Elder, and of Shepherds-purſe, doth alſo well with it. But above all things keep the Patient warm, and let by no means any of the aboveſaid ſteams grow cold on the ſore part.</p>
               <p>Make alſo a Decoction of Garlick, and pour it hot into your cloſe-ſtool, let the Patient ſit upon it, to receive
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60082:46"/>
the hot ſteams. Beſides, put ſome burnt Hartshorn in a linnen cloth, and ſo ſtrew it upon the fundament, by little and little to draw it up. Or heat an Oaken-board very well, and cover it over with Stags-ſuet, and let the Patient ſit upon it whilſt 'tis hot. Put <hi>Colophonium</hi> or the Roſin of Pine-tree upon a heated Iron, and let the Patient by holding his fundament over it take in the ſteams thereof. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint alſo the part with Butter, in which Onions have been boiled; and ſtrew upon it <hi>Album-graecum</hi> very fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pulveriſed. You may alſo make a Salve of Ceruſe, Bol Armeniack, Dragons-blood, Stags-ſuet, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Oyl of Myrrh, or Butter in which firſt hath been boiled broad Plantain, Mullein, or wild Tanſie Silver-weed; and with this anoint the fundament.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Mariſca's,</hi> which do tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Men eſpecially, they may be cured with Oyl of Eggs, Salve of red Hounds-tongue, as alſo with the <hi>Unguentum Populeum,</hi> or with Butter
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60082:47"/>
ſtirr'd up and down in a Leaden Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, till it turn grey or blackiſh. Let the Patient drink alſo of <hi>Scrophularia</hi> or Fig-wort, infuſed in his drink, this being a ſpecific for that evil. Alſo the Oyl of Mullein, Elder-bloſſoms, Water-lilly, and White-lillies, is an excellent remedy for it, a rag dipped therein being laid upon the part affected. To uſe ſcarifying on the lower part of the back-bone, is alſo very good, though it be very painful.</p>
               <p>If the Hoemorrhoid-vein bleed in a convenient time, and do not over-bleed, it is an exceeding good thing, and preſerves from many Diſeaſes, as the Inflammation of the Lungs, Stit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the ſides, the Leproſie, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, Quartans, and the like. If the ſame vein ſhould bleed in one that is mad, or diſturbed in his mind, or in one that is troubled with the Inflammation of the Kidneys, theſe Diſtempers would thereby be allayed. But if it ſhould bleed too often and too violently, it weakens much,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60082:47"/>
cauſeth a pale colour and the Dropſie. My Collegues and I have often open'd it by Leeches, and thereby found great benefit. But in caſe it ſhould exceed in bleeding, you muſt deal with it as you do with the Bloody Flux, and give to the Patient <hi>Terra Sigillata, Bol Armeniack,</hi> burnt Harts-horn, and the like adſtringent things. If you can get ſome teeth of the <hi>Hippo-potamus,</hi> raſp it into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and drink ſome of it in red or white wine; it ſtops all bleeding, of the noſe, mouth, guts, fundament, hoemorrhoids, the matrix, eſpecially the bleeding of Women after deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
               <p>Here is alſo very uſeful the expreſs'd Juyce of Plantain, Shepherds-purſe, and of the tender leaves of Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, or Brambles, infuſed in wine and drunk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60082:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Peſtilential Boyls, Ulcers, Carbuncles, and other venomous Sores.</head>
               <p>ABove I have preſcribed ſome, both Preſervative and Curative, Medicines againſt the Plague, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for this place the <hi>Chirurgical</hi> means, to be uſed againſt that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, thinking it beſt to diſcourſe of them together in a place apart.</p>
               <p>Concerning then the Peſtilential Bubo's and Sores, that riſe behind the Ears, under the Arms, and about the Groin, the Cure of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts chiefly in this, that they be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd with ſpeed; for which end are to be employed meer emollient and ſuppurating things. Yet are you to know to diſtinguiſh between Boyls, there being ſome of them that are not venomous, eſpecially in young people; and they may be hereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, that at the touch they cauſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60082:48"/>
no pain, whereas the Peſtilential ones are very painful; which are alſo diſcover'd by the accompanying venomous Feaver, and other pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Symptoms. And of theſe latter great care muſt be had to bring them out, and to a ſpeedy maturation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe that lye deep are very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
               <p>Some there have been, that have uſed Scarification, and even Veſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, thereby thinking to fetch out the venom. Others have pierced the Sores through, about a hands breadth beneath the Sores, putting the root of black Helebore into them, thereby to draw out the venomous matter. But ſuch means have rather irritated the evil, cauſed great pains, and put the Patient to greater danger.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I judge nothing ſafer and better, than, as I was intimating, to uſe <hi>Emollients.</hi> Take then of the common Diachylon, and lay it upon the invenom'd Boyls; and beſides make a pulſe of theſe herbs, <hi>viz.</hi> of Camomile, Mallows, Melilot, Dill,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60082:49"/>
Line-ſeed, Fenu-greek, Althaea, the roots of White Lillies, as alſo ſalve of Althaea, Oyl of Camomile and Lillies, mixing a little Saffron with it, and ſome Oly of Scorpions. Of this pulſe make ſome warm, and lay it over the Diachylon upon the Sore.</p>
               <p>Or, boil Wheaten-bread in the broath of Mallows and Camomile, till it grow ſoft, then ſaffron it over, and mix March-mallows-ſalve with it, and lay it on. Or make a Plaiſter of Figgs and roſted Onions; or, make a pulſe of Bread-leaven, Honey, yolks of Eggs, and the juyce of Onions, adding a little Turpentine to it, and ſo lay it on.</p>
               <p>If the meer common <hi>Diachylon</hi> be not ſufficient, uſe the Plaiſter <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chylon cum gummis</hi> or <hi>de Mucilagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> or mix a Melilot-plaiſter with the common Diachylon, make a pulſe of it with Oyl of Lillies, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little Oyl of Scorpions with it, and ſo lay it on.</p>
               <p>In laying on of Treacle, I have this conſideration, that Treacle hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60082:49"/>
putrefaction, which is the thing here moſt of all deſired, becauſe all maturation, which here is a reducing the Sore to ſuppuration, is a kind of putrefaction.</p>
               <p>Here alſo the Plaiſter call'd <hi>Baſilicon</hi> is of good uſe; likewiſe the <hi>Ceratum Oeſipum Philagrii</hi> and <hi>Meſuae,</hi> which <hi>Cerata</hi> are made of <hi>Gummi Ammoniac, Bdellium, Turpentine,</hi> liquid <hi>Styrax, Gooſe-greaſe, Marrow of Cows-bones</hi> and <hi>Oeſipum,</hi> and a little Saffron. Some take a dried Toad, and lay it upon the boyl, to draw out the venom.</p>
               <p>Now when the Sores are ſoftned and ripe, and yet break not of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are to be opened with a lancet; and if you have to do with Perſons ſo delicate that they cannot endure a lancet, you may make uſe of the <hi>Lapis Septicus</hi> or Corroſive-ſtone, which opens without pain, but is more ſlow. Mean time beware of opening the Sores too ſoon; for then they will turn to a hard ſwelling, which the Patient will not wear off whilſt he liveth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60082:50"/>There are alſo ſome Plague-ſores that never break, but wear away by ſweat. Yet if they ſhould leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind ſome hardneſs, you may, when the danger is paſt and the ſickneſs overcome, make uſe of ſome fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Melilot, Camomile, March-mallows, Mullein and ſuch like: You may alſo take of the Gum, call'd <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camahaca,</hi> and mix with it a Plaiſter of Melilot or Diachylon, and lay it on.</p>
               <p>The Sores being open'd, they muſt be kept open with ſmall pellets, (called by the <hi>Germans, Quellmaiſſeln,</hi>) dipt in a Salve made for this purpoſe out of freſh Butter, Yolks of Eggs, and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, well mixt together cold.</p>
               <p>But it happens ſometimes, that ſuch <hi>Bubo's,</hi> by reaſon of the venomous matter, do eat in, or grow fiſtulous, or make matter-baggs, in which the matter ſettles. In this caſe you muſt uſe the <hi>Unguentum fuſcum, Apoſtolicum,</hi> or the <hi>Aegyptiacum:</hi> Or make the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing water, to be ſquirted into ſuch Sores; namely of Celondine, <hi>Scordium</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60082:50"/>
or Water-germander, <hi>Carduus-bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus,</hi> Centory, or the like Herbs, together with Tormentil and Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-graſs; all boiled in wine. If the Sores be very ill, you may boil with it ſome quick Brimſtone, and Myrrh, and, if need be, mix with it a little fine Verdigreaſe. Or, take Honey four ounces and an half, a quarter of an ounce of <hi>Aloes Epatica,</hi> a drachm of Salt, an ounce and a half of Scordium, mix all well together, and keep it for uſe; and when you have occaſion for any of it, then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it in wine, and ſpirt it in. Mean time, enlarge the opening of the Boyls with the aforeſaid pellets, that ſo the matter may have vent enough, and come away without any impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The Unguent of <hi>Ulyſſes Aldrovan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> is alſo very good, for the clearing of ſuch Sores; and 'tis made of Oyl of Roſes, the Juyce of broad Plantain, ſharp-pointed Dock, Centory, and Night-ſhade, with a little Litharge, burnt Lead, and prepared Camphir.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60082:51"/>
Inſtead of the Juyce of Night-ſhade you may take that of Cumfry.</p>
               <p>As for the Sores call'd <hi>Anthraces,</hi> and thoſe they call Carbuncles, great care muſt be taken to break them ſoon, and to heal them ſlowly, that ſo the poiſonous matter may all come away. They ripen and break ſooneſt by fatty (but not hot) Plaiſters and Unguents; eſpecially ſuch as are made of butter, leaven, yolks of Eggs and Honey; or if you mix together Turpentine, <hi>Unguentum Populeum,</hi> or Roſe-ſalve mixt with yolks of Eggs, or the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum Anodynum</hi> mixt with the Ointment of Hounds-tongue, and laid on it. It muſt be often refreſhed, becauſe ſuch hot Sores and Ulcers, before they break, do ſo draw, waſte, and, as 'twere, lick up thoſe fatneſſes, that ſometimes of the plaiſters, that have lain on them, there remains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the bare ragg. The <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſtrum Baſilicon,</hi> or the common yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low drawing plaiſter, is here the moſt uſeful.</p>
               <p>You muſt alſo ſurround the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrax</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60082:51"/>
with good defenſives; for if it invade the neighbouring part never ſo little, it will ſoon make a large <hi>halo</hi> or circle, which will at length ſeparate from the ſound, and fall away like an <hi>eſcarre.</hi> For ſuch defenſives make uſe of <hi>Album Campho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum,</hi> or the <hi>Unguentum de Liqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia,</hi> known by our people under the name of <hi>Dr.</hi> Mindererus <hi>his Lico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-ointment. Item</hi> the <hi>Unguentum de Lithargyro;</hi> or the <hi>Unguentum Jovis,</hi> prepared of freſh Butter, with <hi>Thla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiminus,</hi> or Bowyers Muſtard, (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Narrow-leaved wild Creſſes,) Cranes-bill, Elder, Poppy, Vervain, and ſome ſhaved Licoriſh. Some take nothing but Vervain and the freſh leaves of Henbane, beaten together, and the Juyce ſtrained, and ſo uſed. Of this Ointment you may make much with confidence; for it will do you very good ſervice in Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, eſpecially in the caſe of the ſwelling of the groins.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the approved Medicines for this purpoſe, may deſervedly be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60082:52"/>
reckoned the plaiſter made of Soot; which is thus to be prepared: Take of the fineſt Chimney-ſoot one ounce and a quarter; of Leaven, Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and freſh Butter, <hi>ana</hi> one ounce; of Venetian Soap an ounce and a half; two yolks of Eggs; of Treacle and Mithridate, <hi>ana</hi> a quarter of an ounce: Beat all theſe together in a mortar; and ſo reduce it to a paſte, and then uſe it plaiſter-wiſe.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Anthrax</hi> or the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle is broken, you muſt then handle it very gently and diſcreetly; uſing only the above deſcribed Egg-ſalve, putting it into the opening, and covering the Sore only with the common yellow drawing plaiſter, or the plaiſter prepared of Oyl, Wax, and Roſin, or Turpentine. Let the matter work out well, and when you are ſure that 'tis very clean, and have a mind to conſolidate it, make only uſe of <hi>Triapharm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>con<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vulgarly call'd the brown <hi>Diachylon;</hi> you may beſides put into it ſome of the <hi>Unguentum de Tutia,</hi> and that of the <hi>Diapompholox</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60082:52"/>
and one of the plaiſters of them upon it. The <hi>Ulme</hi>-plaiſter alſo, made of Oyl and Ceruſe, heals alſo very well. But be very careful, leſt any of the matter remain lurking in the Ulcer. If here and there any ſhould be found yet remaining, as often happens, then make uſe of the <hi>Emplaſtrum Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> But if you can prepare the <hi>Diapalma,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Diacalci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thros,</hi> make uſe of that. I am wont to call it the <hi>Fiſtula</hi>-plaiſter, becauſe it doth not eaſily ſuffer <hi>Fiſtula's</hi> to ſtink, but keeps them clean and ſweet. Such a plaiſter is alſo that, which is called <hi>Iſis,</hi> to be found in <hi>Galen,</hi> and performing the ſame thing. They are both to be found in the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Diſpenſatory, together with the way of preparing them.</p>
               <p>Now what concerns <hi>Old</hi> Sores, which many are troubled with, in their Leggs eſpecially, becauſe the humors of the body uſually ſettle there; you muſt above all things be careful to keep them clean, and to that end waſh them, at leaſt once a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60082:53"/>
day, with your own urine: Or boil <hi>Carduus-benedictus,</hi> Egrimony, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and roots of Tormentil, in half ſmall meath and half wine, and waſh the Ulcer with it, as often as you dreſs it. Among the common plaiſters for ſuch evils is the brawn <hi>Diachylum</hi> one of the beſt. Elſe you may prepare this Ointment which follows: Take the middle rind of Elder, and St. <hi>Johns</hi>-wort, boil them in oyl, putting a little wine to it, and ſo let it boil up till the wine be boiled away; then take it off from the fire, and let it cool; this done, ſtir a little Turpentine amongſt it, and a yolk or two of Eggs, according as you make a greater or leſſer quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; mixing with it a little Allum, and Vitriol, (the white is the beſt) ſtir all well together, and apply it to the Ulcer, and make a bandage, and cover it as uſually. For a good Drawing-plaiſter, take Roſin, Bee-wax and Oyl-olive; the quantity of the Roſin muſt be but the half of the Wax: Let them melt together, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60082:53"/>
ſtir amongſt it ſome Tartar exquiſitly powder'd. Uſe not much of fatty things to ſuch Ulcers. I have had under my care ſuch Ulcers, that were to be healed with only dry things, as with ſtrewing in of <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> and the red Earth of Vitriol, of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>For this reaſon the antient Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians and Chirurgions invented a dry Stone, which they kept ſo ſecret, that they called it <hi>Lapis Philoſophorum;</hi> which is eaſily made, as followeth: Take Allum, Hungarian Vitriol, of each one pound; beat them to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and mix them well together; then put all into a glaſed earthen pot, and pour upon it two quarts of water, boil them together, and ſtir them continually with a <hi>Spatula,</hi> taking off the ſcurn: When 'tis boiled in, put to it an ounce of <hi>Bolus Armenus,</hi> an ounce and a half of Ceruſe, a quarter of an ounce of Camphir, all finely powder'd, ſtirring it well about; laſtly put it to a quart of ſharp Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and boil all together to a ſtony
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60082:54"/>
conſiſtence; which reduce to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and of it ſtrew a little into the Ulcer, or let ſome of it diſſolve in a convenient liquor, and waſh the Ulcer therewith, or dip ſome linnen raggs in it, and lay it over the place.</p>
               <p>'Tis alſo prepared this way: Take green and white Vitriol, of each a drachm; of <hi>Lapis calaminaris,</hi> Ceruſe, Bol Armeniac, of each two ounces and a half; of Sal Armoniac an ounce. Beat them all to powder, put them in an earthen pot, mingle and ſtir them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Vineger, to be a thick pulſe; then put your pot upon a hot charcoal-fire, to let it grow red hot, ſo as that the matter be reduced to a ſtony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence; of which diſſolve about half an ounce in half a pint of water, dip linnen raggs into it, and put it twice a day upon the Ulcer. 'Tis alſo very good for purulent Breaſts.</p>
               <p>I was ſpeaking above of <hi>Lave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> Theſe you may prepare of all ſorts of Wound-herbs, by boiling Conſound, Bugle, Fluellin, Ground-ivy, Yarrow, Snake-weed, Avens,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60082:54"/>
Arſmare; you may alſo, againſt putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and the ſettling of purulent matter, mix ſometimes a little Myrrh, or <hi>Aloes Epatica,</hi> Frankincenſe, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, quick Brimſtone, Camphir, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Allum, Vitriol, or the like. Nor is it need to bind your ſelf to this or that preciſely, but you may take ſuch of them as you can get.</p>
               <p>I have a peculiar Ulcer-ſalve, which I call <hi>Unguentum Decameron,</hi> being made of ten ſorts of Juices. Of theſe the principal is the Juice of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicaria,</hi> (Arſmart;) to which are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Juices of Groundſel, Tobacco, Yarrow, ſharp-pointed Dock, Cranes-bill, broad and pointed Plantain, Centory, St. <hi>Johns</hi>-wort, and Celon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine. Theſe Juices muſt be well ſtrained, and then kept for ſome days in glaſſes or glaſed veſſels to ſettle; and then very gently pour off the clear from the ſediment. Which done, boil them with freſh butter, and ſome good Licoriſh newly ſcraped, as alſo ſome Tormentil and Cumfrey, adding a little red Hounds-tongue ſalve and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60082:55"/>
Oyl of Myrrh, and Deer-ſuet: Let all be boiled together, till the cracking ceaſe, and the Juice be boiled in. Then ſtrain it through a linnen cloth, and add to it ſome Venice-Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Gum <hi>Elemi</hi> and a little Bees-wax, both the latter melted each a part. Of the Wax there needs no more than to bring the Salve to a due conſiſtence. Then is this Unguent prepared, to which may be added a little refined Verdigreaſe, which will make it perfect. It is of great efficacy in foul wounds, for both cleanſing and healing; as experience will ſhew.</p>
               <p>A Chirurgion, in meeting with Ulcers, is to obſerve well the purulent matter that iſſues, ſince he may from thence learn the condition of the evil, whether it proceed from foul blood, gall, corrupt phlegm, or aduſt melancholy. If the evil grow worſe, and the humors of the body force their way copiouſly thorow, then beware, and withall exhort the Patient to purge, or to ſweat with taking ſome Saſſafraſs, or the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60082:55"/>The <hi>Sanies</hi> or matter that is thick, white, and well digeſted, is the beſt; but when there runs but a ſharp water out of the Ulcer, this is not good, and is withall painful. Which to obviate, you muſt uſe Litharge, Ceruſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the like; putting alſo beaten Lead upon the place, and cleanſing the fiſtulat holes with Lead-oyl, qualifying its ſharpneſs with Oyl of Eggs. This Lead-oyl is made two ways, the one out of Ceruſſe, which is green; the other out of Litharge, which is yellow or reddiſh. Both are prepared with Vineger.</p>
               <p>Boil <hi>Celondine</hi> in wine, and with this wine you may alſo cleanſe the Ulcer with good effect. Mix after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a drachm of Verdigreaſe with about four ounces of the Juyce of Ground-Ivy; uſe it with wiecks or raggs dipt therein for the foul Ulcer-holes.</p>
               <p>Burn Oyſter-ſhells to powder, and uſe it for old Ulcers that need clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which this powder will well perform by reaſon of the Salt that is
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60082:56"/>
in thoſe ſhells. You may ſometimes have occaſion alſo of the <hi>Mercurius praecipitatus,</hi> or the <hi>Mercurius dulcis Coſmeticus.</hi> If you can prepare this, you have a good Remedy.</p>
               <p>As for hard Knobs and Boyls, they commonly owing their riſe to the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereal Diſeaſe are not ſo proper for this place. However you may make a plaiſter againſt ſuch Knobs of the phlegm of Althaea or Marſh-mallows, Gummi Ammoniac, Galbanum, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, Myrrh, Miſſel-toe of the oak, mixing a little Bee-wax therewith and ſome Oyl of Earth-worms. If you will have it ſtronger, mix with it Gumm Elemi, Tacamahaca or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rana. But this can only be compaſſed by the rich men; the poor muſt be content with the Melilot-plaiſter, mixt with Saffron and the Oyl of Mullain or Dill. You may alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for ſuch Patients a Salve of Fox-oyl, Dill-oyl, Turpentine, Man-greaſe, and the like, mixing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſome Oyl of Earth-worms and the Oyl of Mullain-flowers, Camomil and white Lillies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:60082:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Chirurgical means of ſtaunching blood, of Wound-balſoms and plaiſters, of Wound-drinks, and remedies for Burnings.</head>
               <p>THis is the moſt neceſſary <hi>Chapter</hi> of this whole Tract. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in every Camp, yea in every Regiment, and even in every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany there ought to be one or more Chirurgions; yet becauſe in a battle, or the ſtorming of a ſtrong-hold, there may be wounded a very great number of men, who, by reaſon of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, cannot all be dreſſed by the Chirurgions, every common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, that is found and un-hurt, is obliged to aſſiſt his fellow, conſidering it may ſoon be his own caſe.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place then, refreſh thy fellow, that is wounded, with wine, cold water, vineger, or the like; then place him in a right poſture.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60082:57"/>
For, if the wounds be in the head or about the breaſt, you ought to lay him high with his head and ſhoulders, that ſo the blood may ſink down from the places wounded. If his legg be hurt, put it ſo that it may not hang downwards, and thereby the afflux from the body be prevented, which otherwiſe might cauſe a tumour. If the wounds be in the middle of the body, then place him ſo, that, if poſſible, he may lye ſomewhat hollow with his back.</p>
               <p>This done, waſh the wound very gently, (ſo as not to anger it,) with meer wine, or even with pure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water, only with a very little ſalt caſt into it; or with the Patients own urine; and then dry it with lint of long-worn linnen, without much ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the wound, for fear of making the veins bleed again.</p>
               <p>If any one do bleed ſo copiouſly, that it is not eaſily ſtopp'd, and the Patient is in danger, then receive of his blood in an Iron pan, and letting it run about therein, hold it over the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60082:57"/>
fire till it be dry and between your fingers friable to powder; of which ſtrew ſome into the bleeding wound, and it will ſtop it. But of this caſe more hereafter.</p>
               <p>The wound being cleanſed, and the bleeding ſtayed, take fine linnen-raggs, burn them as you are wont to do for tinder, and quench it in Oyl of Olives; and put ſome of it into the wound. If you have no plaiſter at hand, take a ſlice of unſalted lard and lay it on. If that be alſo wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, dip a pledget of linnen-raggs in warm wine, and being wrung out very dry, lay it upon the wound, and a dry bandage over it, that ſo the moiſt pledget may long keep warm. Though in ſuch wounds, as are apt to bleed much, warm bandages are often to be avoided, and ſometimes (but with ſingular care and diſcretion) cold bandages to be uſed, if the hurt be not in the brain, breaſt or bowels. Whence old <hi>Hippocrates</hi> hath this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm: <hi>Frigido verò in iis locis uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, unde ſanguis aut fluit aut fluxunus eſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60082:58"/>
Yet this muſt be done with great caution, leſt in the place affected there ſhould follow a Gangrene.</p>
               <p>After this, take Oyl of Olives and Wine, beat them well together, and warm the mixture; dip in it linnen pledgets, wring them dry, and lay them on warm with a dry bandage over it. This muſt be done once every hour or every two hours; nor let this care and labour ſeem irkſome to you, for it will have a good effect.</p>
               <p>This Dreſs is almoſt the only thing, which the <hi>Knights</hi> of <hi>Maltha</hi> make uſe of at Sea to heal their wounds; for the Oyl allays the pain and the ſwelling, as the Wine cleanſeth, and theſe two together cauſe healing. Whence the <hi>Samaritan</hi> in the Goſpel is ſaid to have poured only Oyl and Wine into the wounds of him, that was fallen among Thieves. You may therefore make out of theſe two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Wound-ſalve that may be equivalent to almoſt every common Wound-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, preparing it thus:</p>
               <p>Take one part of Oyl-olive, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60082:58"/>
two parts of Wine, boil them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till the Wine be boiled in, and the Oyl, when any is thrown into the fire, cracks no more; and you have a Wound-oyl according to wiſh: Put of it with fine linnen ſhavings into the wound, and it will, for a plain remedy, do marvels.</p>
               <p>You may alſo melt Lard unſalted, mix it with Honey and Rye flower, and ſo make it into a Salve, which, though plain and ſimple, may, when put upon the wound; have as good an effect, as many Plaiſters that are in great eſteem.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe, for a very good Wound-ſalve, take of the beſt <hi>Aloes</hi> cleanly pulveriſed the weight of a ducat, mingle and ſtir it with half an ounce of fine honey; melt afterwards by it ſelf half an ounce of Deer-ſuet, and ſtir it among the other Ingredients: Thus you have a good Salve againſt the putrefaction of wounds, and for the aſſwaging of their pains, as alſo for healing them, if you duely apply it to the wound: If you'l add to it
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60082:59"/>
a little Cyprus-Turpentin with the yolk of an Egg, you may.</p>
               <p>The black Wheel-greaſe in a time of need is alſo a good Wound ſalve, and is only deſpiſed becauſe of its plainneſs. When you uſe it, lay only over it the leaves of Snake-weed, or of pointed Plantain.</p>
               <p>But by all means keep the wound clean, and let not many look into it, for fear they ſhould by their breath annoy it; ſome being faſting, others having eaten one thing, others ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But eſpecially admit not many women, when you open the wound for cleanſing and dreſſing it. But above all things take care, to exclude the Air as much as is poſſible from the open'd wound, eſpecially if any Artery or Nerve be hurt. Take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that Carpenters and Joyners, when they have hurt themſelves, do almoſt by this only means of well cloſing their wounds and keeping out the Air, heal themſelves. They take a very thin chip, and lay upon it ſome of the glue, wherewith they joyn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60082:59"/>
the boards of their work, and this they apply to the wound, firſt well cleanſed, and let it lye on, till it fall off of it ſelf, and the wound is healed. But this will not do in caſe any Bones be hurt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> take Honey and the Duſt-flower of the Mills, freſh Butter and Bol-armeniack, and knead it well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, without any fire, until it be as thick as a Plaiſter, and this laid on, is very good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> take Cumphrey well clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, out it ſmall, add to it one or two of the Vulnerary Herbs, ſuch as you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et with in the field, as <hi>Pyrola</hi> or Winter-green, Yarrow, Plantain, Fluellin, Orpin, Confound, Sanible, Bugle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Boil this in Linſeed-oyl and a little Wine, until the Wine is boiled away; and this being ſtrained, put to it ſome raw Honey and one or two well beaten yolks of Eggs, (according to the quantity you make) and a little Turpentin, and ſo thruſt it, with ſome Hemp or Flax dipt in it, into the wound.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60082:60"/>Lime-water is one of the ſimpleſt on plaineſt remedies, but healeth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably well. Take only ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaked Lime, pour on it clear water, and let it ſtand upon it till the Lime be fallen to the bottom: Waſh the wound with it, eſpecially ſuch as are old running Sores, and you'l find a wonderful effect.</p>
               <p>Theſe plain means may be raiſed, in caſe you want a Chirurgion, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the aſſiſtance of your Fellow-ſouldier in the application; though thoſe very remedies may challenge a place among the moſt chargeablednes, preſcribed and applied by Maſters. And provided the Chirurgion do not under-value theſe my plain and cheap remedies, but receive them thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, I am ready, here to teach him ſome ways, hitherto concealed by me, which I ſcruple to keep any longer from publick knowledge.</p>
               <p>Know then firſt, that to a Phyſitian belongs alſo the knowledge of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, as a third part of the Art of Medicine, the other two being the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60082:60"/>
                  <hi>Pharmaceutica,</hi> preſcribing Medicines for inward Diſeaſes, and the <hi>Diate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> ordering the Patients Diet and other neceſſaries. I have my ſelf, whilſt I practiſed Phyſick, dreſſed in Camps many wounds with my own hands and cured them, carrying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways my Chirurgical <hi>apparatus</hi> about me, without any diſparagement to my Profeſſion; imitating herein the Examples, above alledged, of <hi>Poda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyrius</hi> and <hi>Machaon,</hi> two of the chief Phyſitians of the Antients in the Army before <hi>Troy,</hi> who were not at all aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to practiſe Chirurgery, and to attend the cure of wounded Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers!</p>
               <p>Firſt of all then, conſider well, whether the wound be mortal or no. Next, what limb or part it is that hath received the wound: The wounds in the Head are commonly the moſt dangerous, by reaſon of the Symptoms incident to them, as the Apoplexy, Falling Sickneſs or other Convulſions, the Palſey and Laming of the limbs by reaſon of the hurt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60082:61"/>
nerves, as alſo Phrenſy, Loſs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and Speech, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are wont to be conſequent, according as the reſpective nerves have been ſtruck or wounded. If the Breaſt be any where wounded, great care alſo is to be had, and the means muſt be directed to prevent purulency (which that place, by reaſon of the heat there, is ſubject to,) and to heal the <hi>pleura</hi> or the inner membrane of the ribbs; the like is to be done concerning the diaphragme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ought alſo to obſerve, what kind of wound it is, you have to do with, whether any bone, any nerve, or artery be hurt; whether it be a meer fleſh-wound, and the like. If it be a gaping wound, you muſt, if it hath taken cold from the Air, bath it with warm wine, and keep it very cloſe; and make uſe of the ſtrong aſtringent plaiſter, prepared of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, Gumm Elemi, Turpentin, Pitch, with ſome Maſtick, Frankincenſe, <hi>Sarcocolla,</hi> as alſo ſome Blood-ſtone, Mummy, and <hi>Crocus Martis</hi> mixt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60082:61"/>
therewith, and keep all on carefully with a good bandage, which is a great matter in all wounds. For, ſome months ſince, I had a Patient under my cure, whoſe Skull in the place of one of its ſutures was ſever'd, ſo as that I found a conſiderable ſpace between the two parts ſeparated. I order'd a Chirurgion of my particular acquaintance to draw thoſe parts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly together with good bandages; which being well done, I cauſed his hair to be ſhorn away, and an aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent plaiſter to be applied, which was almoſt like a Rupture-plaiſter; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in three or four weeks, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of many, my Patient was perfectly healed. This plaiſter was the <hi>Ceratum expelle arietina,</hi> mixt with Gumm <hi>Elemi,</hi> and with a little <hi>Cera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de Betonica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt alſo be provided with good Blood-ſtaunching remedies. The common ones are, <hi>Bol-armeniac, Sheep-trickles, Blood-ſtone, Tragacanth. Terra Sigillata, Mill-duſt, Hares-hair, Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks-dung, &amp;c.</hi> Avoid by all means
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60082:62"/>
Cauſticks, eſpecially Sublimat, Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic, Colcothar; with which you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a wound, and caſt the Patient into very dangerous ſymptoms: For, though they may by their corroſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at firſt aſtringe the wound, yet they do afterwards ſo fret and eat it, that you would think, hell-fire were in it. Beware alſo of a hot Iron, which many have a refuge to as to a Maſter-piece and the laſt remedy.</p>
               <p>Among the chief Aſtringents, is <hi>Frog-ſpawn;</hi> which therefore you are, when 'tis in ſeaſon, to make good proviſion of, for the whole year. Take therefore in the Spring a lump of raggs, and dip it into Smiths-water, in which firſt ſome crude Allum hath been diſſolved. Let this lump be dried again, and then draw it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the Spawn of Frogs, ſo as that the Spawn may every where hang on it, and expoſe it to the Air to dry; and afterwards draw the ſame again thorough Frog-ſpawn: Which repeat as often as you can, during the ſeaſon of Frog-ſpawn; for the oftner
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60082:62"/>
you dip the raggs into it, the more vertue they will receive. This Spawn ſtauncheth bleeding, with a good bandage. I have often uſed with good ſucceſs the diſtilled water of Frog-ſpawn in the bleeding of the Noſe, firſt mixt with crude Allum, and then drawn up into the Noſtrils. Take a green Frog, burn him in a pipkin, not to aſhes, but ſo as to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to powder: This powder put into a ſmall Taffaty-bagg, and hang it about the neck of a woman that floods exceſſively; and ſhe will find great help from it.</p>
               <p>Having often made mention of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, which is one of the chief reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for ſtopping of blood, I will make publick the <hi>Magiſtery of Allum,</hi> which I have hitherto kept ſecret. Take then of the beſt and cleareſt Allum as much as you pleaſe; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſe it, and put the powder into an Oxe- or Swines-bladder, tying it very cloſe: Then throw it into a kettle of hot water, and the Allum will be diſſolved; this Solution bring over
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60082:63"/>
the helm out of a low retort, until the Allum get a <hi>caput mortuum;</hi> then ceaſe to urge the fire any more, leſt you force corroſive ſpirits from it, which are noxious to our preſent purpoſe. This <hi>caput mortuum</hi> put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into a bladder, and diſſolve it as before; and do this ſo long, until the whole body of your Allum be brought over the helm. But you muſt filter the firſt ſolution, for fear of any duſt or other heterogeneous matter mixt with it.</p>
               <p>This is the Magiſtery of Allum, able to draw the veins together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corroſion. Apply this to wounds, or any other bleeding part. You may mix with it Tragacanth, Gummi A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabic, <hi>Sanguis Draconis,</hi> and well-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Whites of Eggs.</p>
               <p>Take good notice, whether the wounded Patient have heated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſtorming a place, or by any other military execution, or whether he be yet diſtemper'd by paſſion; for, as long as this laſts, the blood is in a rage, and can hardly be ſtopped
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60082:63"/>
In this caſe ſtop the wound with Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks dung; and take Vineger and Whites of Eggs well beaten toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a little Allum, and refined Salt-peter; put to it as much Frog-ſpawn, Shepherds purſe, broad Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or other convenient water, as is neceſſary; ſo that there may be three parts of water and one part of vineger; dip pledgets into it, and clap them cold to the wound, and the bleeding will ceaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crocus Martis</hi> alſo is an excellent ſtauncher of blood, to be uſed both inwardly and outwardly. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly it cureth the Bloody Flux and other Fluxes; and outwardly applied to wounds and ſtrewed into them, it cloſeth the veins. But it muſt not be prepared with <hi>Aqua-fortis,</hi> or diſtilled Vineger, or any corroſive thing, but only by the heat of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberating furnace; and afterwards diſtill often from it ſome proper water, as of <hi>Roſes, Speed-well, Self-heal</hi> or broad <hi>Plantain;</hi> after which prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration it is divers times to paſs again
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60082:64"/>
through a reverberating furnace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it grow as light as a down-feather: And then 'tis fit for our purpoſe; for as long as it is ſtrong and heavy, the body of it is not throughly opened.</p>
               <p>Among other things, you may make uſe of the Red earth of Vitriol; which is to be thus prepared: Take Vitriol, as much as you pleaſe, put it, in a new unglaſed pipkin, into a Potters oven, to deprive it of its moiſture, and to reduce it to a <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cothar:</hi> Then pulveriſe this calcined Vitriol, and in a large glaſed earthen diſh pour hot water on it, letting it ſtand ſo for four or five hours; then decant the water, and pour other hot water upon it, as before, repeating this three, four, or five times, until all the ſalt be got out of the ſaid <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cothar;</hi> which whether it be done, may eaſily be found by the taſte. Then dry this red dulcified Earth, and it will prove a very good blood ſtaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching medicine; which may alſo in other caſes be variouſly uſed; as you'l find it hereafter of great uſe in my
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60082:64"/>
plaiſter for wounds made by thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
               <p>The water you had poured on this <hi>Colcothar,</hi> you ought not to throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as uſeleſs, but to put it by; and, for other occaſions, you may boil it away, and it will leave a Salt behind, as white as ſnow, with which you may do wonders in foul Sores. I have uſed it with good ſucceſs in ſuch caſes; in which it cleanſeth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a firm ground for new and good fleſh to grow, upon. For, though there be many things, that cleanſe Sores, yet they leave the fleſh looſe and ſpung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; but this is both aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and withall maketh ſuch a found and firm bottom, that you may truſt to it: Whence alſo it is to be uſed in fiſtulous Sores.</p>
               <p>But to return to the ſtopping of Blood; take the blood of a Lamb or Sheep, let it ſtand in a clean earthen veſſel, until the <hi>ſerum</hi> be ſever'd from it; pour this off, and dry the blood well in a new glaſed pipkin, upon hot embers; Then pulveriſe it, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60082:65"/>
mix with it a fourth part of clean pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſed <hi>Tragacanth,</hi> and ſtrew this into the wound. If the iſſue of the blood be ſo impetuous, that it waſhes away the firſt application, then wipe the wound again, and ſtrew into it of the ſame powder the ſecond time. Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting amongſt it Allum, <hi>Crocus Martis,</hi> or the red Earth of Vitriol, you will do well: Bind the wound with the <hi>Emplaſtrum Santalinum,</hi> (which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Incognitum</hi> by our Chirurgions,) or with the <hi>Ceratum ex pelle arietinae,</hi> due to <hi>Arnoldus de Villa nova.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The blood being ſtopt, and the wound cleanſed, you muſt then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply good vulnerary Oyls or Wound-balſoms. Oyls are all, as I mention'd above; fatty; whence it is, that they do not eaſily conſolidate wounds, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you put to them ſome refined <hi>Maſtic, Sarco-colla, Sanguis Draconis, Sandarach,</hi> or the like.</p>
               <p>But to open unto you the good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of my heart, I ſhall deſcribe here my Wound-balſom, wherewith I have, by Gods aſſiſtance, done much good; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:60082:65"/>Take as much as you pleaſe of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentin of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> which comes from <hi>Venice,</hi> and is taken inwardly; and the ſame quantity of the red Oyl of St. <hi>Johns</hi> wort, diſſolve them together! Then take Gumm Elemy, diſſolve it apart, and pour it among the other; and ſo let all cool, and when 'tis half cold, pour amongſt it a little Oyl of Bees-wax, and your Balſom is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. I cannot tell you the preciſe weight of each ingredient, becauſe as often as I have prepared it, I have done it by the Eye, and as it ſeemed good unto me; only note, that there muſt be ſo much of the Gumm Elemy as to give it a due conſiſtence; which you may try, by caſting a drop or two of it into cold water; this Balſom being to be thinner than an Unguent, and yet thicker than Oyl.</p>
               <p>This Balſom heals very ſpeedily, eſpecially when uſed in wounds freſhly inflicted, on fine pledgets, and only with a yellow Tractif bound over it.</p>
               <p>Be alſo provided with good Plaiſter for wounds made by Thruſting, ſuch
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60082:66"/>
as are the <hi>Opodeldoch</hi> of <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> or the good black Thruſt plaiſter, thus to be prepared: Take of Oyl of Roſe ſeven ounces; of <hi>Colophonium,</hi> black Pitch, white Wax, Roman Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, Ceruſſe, Frankincenſe, Myrth, <hi>ana</hi> eight ounces, of Maſtic, one ounce; of the Oyl of Eggs, two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; of Spike-oyl, one ounce, of the Oyl of Juniper-berries, three ounces; of <hi>Mumia,</hi> two ounces; off white Vitriol and red Corals, <hi>ana</hi> two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; of <hi>Heron</hi>-ſuet, one ounce; of Magnet, two ounces; of well clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Earth-worms pulveriſed and of Camphir, <hi>ana</hi> one ounce: Of all this make a powder <hi>ſecundùm artem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My <hi>Opodeldoch,</hi> that I make uſe of, is almoſt like this, but that I mix with it the red Earth of the Oyl of Vitriol, above ſpoken of in the matter of Blood-ſtaunching; and add alſo to it Turpentin and Gumm <hi>Elemi,</hi> with ſome <hi>Tutia, Aloes epatica,</hi> well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>Lapis Calaminaris,</hi> and <hi>Crocus Martis:</hi> And thus the Plaiſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes red and hard, like <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:60082:66"/>
Sealing-wax. I take alſo <hi>Gummi Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniac, Galbanum</hi> and <hi>Opoponax,</hi> the Oyl of <hi>St. Johns-wort</hi> and <hi>Myrrh.</hi> This Plaiſter draws from the bottom, and reaches deep. A Souldier, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this about him, and, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, working it only to ſome flatneſs, there being no need of laying it on a cloth, may thus put it on the wound, taking it off mornings and evenings to wipe it clean; and then working it through again, lay it on as before: And ſo he may heal himſelf; which when done, let him clean the Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and role it up in a bladder, for another occaſion.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen conſiderable operations of Gumm Elemi uſed alone, laid on leather, and put upon the thruſt; but this wound is then to be kept from falling together.</p>
               <p>To prevent incidental heat and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation of the wounds, make uſe of the Oyl of Roſes, Bol Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niac, Whites of Eggs and Camphir. But to avoid trouble, you may find ready, in the Apothecary-ſhops, the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60082:67"/>
                  <hi>Unguentum album, Unguentum de Minlo, Camphoratum de Liguiritia, de Lithar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyro, Santalinum,</hi> and the like; to be put about the wound when dreſſed.</p>
               <p>You may with great benefit, and you ought alſo, eſpecially in the wounds of the Head, provided there be no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of bleeding, lay over the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage ſome fine raggs moiſten'd in wine, and well dried again. This allays the pain, and withall prevents ſwelling.</p>
               <p>And in caſe the wound be ſwelled, you may alſo to good purpoſe make uſe of Fomentations, made of the herb and flowers of <hi>Mullein, Betony, Egrimony, Cowſlips, Camomil, Melilot, Ground-ivy, red Roſes, Bugle,</hi> and the like: But beware of all hot things, whatever they be. Boil the aforeſaid herbs or the like in half wine and water; but if the wound be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, take two parts of wine and one of water. With ſuch fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations I have done much good; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others upon a Fencing-Maſter of <hi>Nurenberg,</hi> called <hi>Cameyſen,</hi> who
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60082:67"/>
in the publick Fencing-ſchool received thruſts in both his Eyes, inſomuch that by reaſon of the great ſwelling that enſued thereupon he loſt all his ſight; but by the uſe of ſuch fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, God bleſſing the means, I recover'd his ſight.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Bone</hi> being broken, ſet it care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and bind it up ſtrongly, having laid upon it <hi>Oxycroceum</hi> or <hi>Emplaſtrum de pelle Arietina.</hi> You may alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſuch wounds with the like fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as before deſcribed.</p>
               <p>On the bank of the <hi>Rhine</hi> is found a Stone in the gravel, call'd <hi>Lapis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buloſus,</hi> which is eaſily reducible to powder: Of this, if you can get it, give to the Patient, whoſe bone is broken, a drachm to be taken in broath, mornings; of which he will find a very good effect.</p>
               <p>In the caſe of a Limb wrenched, clap to it <hi>Bran</hi> boiled in wine, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, according to occaſion, mixing with it a little Salt, and <hi>Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows</hi> or red <hi>Hounds-tongue-ſalve.</hi> If it have happened long ago, then
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60082:68"/>
make a pulſe of Wheaten-flower, Milk, and the Oyl of <hi>Camomil</hi> or <hi>Mullein,</hi> mixing a little Saffron with it, and clap it on hot. If there be any collection or coagulation of blood, the Unguent of Hounds-tongue will do well, together with a linnen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs moiſtened in warm wine.</p>
               <p>You muſt alſo be provided with good Wound-drinks; but they muſt be prepared diverſly, according to the ſeveral places wounded. Thus in the wounds of the Head, <hi>Betony</hi> challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the pre-eminence and the greateſt quantity of all the Vulnerary Herbs; in the wounds of the Sides, <hi>Carduus benedictus</hi> claims that right; in the wounds of the Breaſt, <hi>Veronica</hi> (or Speedwell) ought to have it; in thoſe about the Kidneys, the Herb Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry muſt be preferred; in thoſe near the Liver, Agrimony will have the precedency, and ſo forth. Mean time, the Vulnerary Herbs, to be uſed in ſuch occaſions, are theſe; <hi>Sanicle, Winter-green, Ladies-mantle, Speedwell, Orpine, Mugwort, Ground-ivy, Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry-leaves,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60082:68"/>
Agrimony, St. Johns-wort, Cinquefoil, Bugle, Tormentil, Snake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weed, Avens, Woodrooff, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may make an excellent Wound-drink of theſe four Ingredients, <hi>viz. Winter-green, Orpine, Mugwort</hi> and <hi>Snakeweed,</hi> boiled in half wine and water; but in caſe there be an inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, wine is to be forborn, or very little of it to be employed.</p>
               <p>If any Bone be broken into ſplinters, do not pull them out with any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but looſen them with a good Ointment of Eggs, keeping the wound open the longer. Nature herſelf will not ſuffer any ſplinter to remain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt be ready with ſome good thing for blood coagulated, in caſe any perſon ſhould have been flung down, ſqueeſed, beaten, or fallen from a high place. The right pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for this purpoſe is thus made: Take of <hi>Terra Sigillata</hi> or <hi>Bol Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niac, Sanguis Draconis</hi> and <hi>Mumia, ana</hi> half an ounce, of <hi>Sperma Ceti</hi> and <hi>Rhubarbana</hi> half a drachm, reduce it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60082:69"/>
to a powder; of which give the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient the weight of about a ducat in wine, or chervil-water. Or take a good quantity of <hi>Chervil,</hi> boil it in meath or fleſh-broath, and let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient drink a good draught of it warm, three times a day. Or let him drink a thimble full of <hi>Sperma Ceti</hi> in beer, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a little butter to it. Or take of <hi>Mumia</hi> half an ounce, of <hi>Sperma Ceti</hi> two drachms, of <hi>Oculi Cancrorum</hi> (of which the blew ones, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fall from Crafiſhes whilſt alive, are the beſt,) three drachms, adding to it a little Licoriſh and Cinnamon, and ſome Tormentil-roots: Of this pulveriſed give every day to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, mornings and evenings, the weight of about half a ducat, and by this means you will expel purulent matter and blood, and bony ſplinters, and ſometimes even bullets lurking in the fleſh; not omitting other good Wound-drinks, and vulnerary Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, Plaiſters, Ointments and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations. Again, take of the red <hi>Hounds-tongue</hi> Ointment, of the bigneſs
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60082:69"/>
of a great Walnut, diſſolve it in warm broath; it expels all coagulated blood, eſpecially if you mix ſome <hi>Sperma Ceti</hi> with it.</p>
               <p>If you have any thorns, thiſtles, bullets, ſmall ſhot, or the like, to draw out, where perhaps you cannot reach them with Inſtruments, then burn live Crafiſhes in a new pipkin, until they be reducible to powder, but burn them not to aſhes. This pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mix with Hares-ſuet, and lay it on, and you will find a good effect. Alſo take the roots of the big <hi>Reed</hi> that grows in mariſhes, dry them to be pulveriſed, and mix Virgin-honey with it, and lay it upon the part; and of the ſame powder give the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to drink, twice a day, the weight of half a ducat in wine, or in broath, or in a vulnerary potion, if you have any at hand. The firſt of this I lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Excellent Doctor <hi>Schleer</hi> of <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The excrement of a <hi>Gander,</hi> being applied, is alſo powerful in drawing out Iron. Again, Quince-wine min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60082:70"/>
with vineger, and putting ſome ſaffron and gun powder amongſt it, if you give it to one that hath been ſhot, it will do him good. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they make a plaiſter of the roots of <hi>Cumfrey, Aron, Polypody, Juniper,</hi> and dried <hi>Radiſhes,</hi> all reduced to powder, and mix it with Hares-ſuet and grey <hi>Diachylum,</hi> making a thick Ointment of it, and ſpreading it over a piece of Hare-skin, and ſo laying it on. This is greatly praiſed, eſpecially when ſeconded with good Wound-drinks, of which <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort</hi> is one of the Ingredients: But if you have not this at hand, take a <hi>Beet</hi> and boil it in wine, and lay it warm on the wound. Likewiſe, young Swallows, not yet fledge, burnt to powder, and this powder made by <hi>acetum</hi> of Roſes into a pulſe, and laid on, does the ſame.</p>
               <p>You ought alſo to be provided for the <hi>Synovia:</hi> And if you proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right with my Wound-balſom above deſcribed, and keep the wound warm, you may therewith do much good.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60082:70"/>
Mix with it, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> the red Earth of Vitriol, above diſcours'd of. This <hi>Synovia</hi> is a dangerous thing, and often cauſeth almoſt intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pain, if it be not well handled; the Herb of Straw-berries and its Juyce have great vertue in this caſe. Some make uſe of the White of Eggs, Bol Armeniac, and the like. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtery of Allum alſo belongs hither; for, Allum mixed with vineger, and clapp'd on very warm, allays it alſo. Elder-bloſſoms likewiſe, uſed every way, are effectual in the ſame caſe. Employ alſo diligently ſuch Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive-plaiſters, as are not fatty, becauſe fat lays no hold on water.</p>
               <p>To proceed to Burnings, I know almoſt no better Salve for burning than this; Take a <hi>Tench,</hi> or any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pond-fiſh; fry one or more of them with good butter, pour the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon cold water in a broad ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then part, and you have an excellent Ointment againſt Burnings. When, ſome years ſince, a Powder-mill was blown up, and the Attendants upon
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60082:71"/>
the work ſo miſerably burnt, that they looked as if they had been roſted, they were healed with this Ointment, only a little finely powder'd <hi>Sage</hi> being mixt with it.</p>
               <p>Cream and Linſeed-oyl mingled together, and raggs, moiſten'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, put upon the burnt part, healeth, though the burning were made with <hi>Aquafortis;</hi> for, to my knowledge, a certain Chymiſt that had thus burnt all his arm, was thereby reſtored. Or, take Oyl of Elder, or ſtale Oyl that hath been long in a burning lamp; beat half as much, as you take of that, of the Whites of Eggs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt it, and anoint the burnt part therewith. If you can get no Oyl of Elder, take any other cooling Oyl, as of <hi>Nymphaea</hi> (Water-lillies) <hi>Poppy-ſeeds, Violets</hi> or <hi>Roſes,</hi> or the Oyl of <hi>Poplar-buds,</hi> or of <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h-marigold</hi> Flowers.</p>
               <p>If you can have Quince-wine, it marvailouſly extinguiſhes the burning of any ſhot, dipping a linnen pledget in it and drawing it through the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60082:71"/>
wound, or left in it, repeating this every twelfth hour. The Juyce or Wine of Quinces muſt be uſed as it comes from the fruit, without any mixture of Sugar. This I learn'd from a Nobleman, a great Souldier, of long experience in the Wars of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Unguentum Jovis,</hi> made of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, Vervain</hi> and <hi>Butter,</hi> is alſo very uſeful for this purpoſe. Likewiſe the Ointment of <hi>Calx viva,</hi> which is firſt ſix or ſeven times to be ſlaked and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with pure water, pouring eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry twelve or ſixteen hours freſh water upon it, and decanting the former, ſo as to leave always the <hi>Calx</hi> at the bottom; which is then to be mixed with Oyl of Roſes, or ſome other cooling Oyl, for an Ointment.</p>
               <p>If you be well acquainted with <hi>Elder,</hi> and know how to uſe it, you may obtain out of it one of the beſt Cures of Burnings, eſpecially out of its middle rinds. Again, Yolks of Eggs and Linſeed-oyl, equal quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, mixt together, and ſpread over
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60082:72"/>
the burning, is alſo very good. Egg-oyl likewiſe uſed by it ſelf, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice employed by Joyners, do well alſo; but the latter of theſe two, if it be mixed with Oyl of <hi>Spicanard,</hi> or <hi>Petroleum,</hi> is to be mingled amongſt <hi>Linſeed-oyl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Spread freſh Butter upon Cabbage-leaves, having firſt fryed the Butter with ſome bloſſoms or the middle rind of <hi>Elder;</hi> and ſo lay them to the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; <hi>Elder</hi> being a great reſiſter of Inflammations, and therefore very good to allay <hi>St. Antonies fire;</hi> if you pull its mild green rinds from the ſtem, and lay them on, without moiſtening them. Elſe they uſe againſt the ſaid Fire, Flower mixed with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Licorice, to be clapt on with a ragg done over with red <hi>Saunders.</hi> My way is, to take the ſhavings of ſome freſh and juycy Licorice, and to fry them in new Butter; then to ſtrain the Butter from it, and to fry the like freſh Licorice therein, and to ſtrain the Butter from that again; repeating this five or ſix times. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60082:72"/>
this ſtrained Butter I ſtir ſome pure and fine <hi>Ceruſſe,</hi> Whites of Eggs and a little Camphire. And with this Ointment I have, by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God, done much good in the ſaid inflammation of <hi>St. Antonies fire;</hi> and the common people do to this very day call this Ointment by no other name than that of Doctor <hi>Minderer</hi>'s <hi>Licorice-ointment.</hi> But to return to the quenching of Burnings.</p>
               <p>If you can have Milk-cream, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it with Cow-dung freſhly made, and ſo clap it on; though freſh Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dung alone allays burning. <hi>Crafiſhes</hi> pounded alive, and fryed in freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or in common Suet, the Butter ſtrained herefrom, is alſo a good Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt burnings. Unſalted Lard, melted by a Wax-candle, or an hot Iron, and dropp'd upon freſh cold water, and then gather'd up from the water, and carefully rubbed from the ſame, hath the like operation. Take one of the cooling Oyls above-named, and freſh Butter, boil the middle rind of Elder in it, and with a ſufficient
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60082:73"/>
quantity of Wax make of it a Salve, and this alſo will cure burning.</p>
               <p>You ought alſo to be provided with a fit <hi>apparatus,</hi> Lints, Swathing-clouts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to take Deer-ſuet, Oyl of Roſes or Elder, and white Wax, and melt them over the fire, yet ſo as that you melt the Wax by it ſelf, and add of it no more to the reſt than to make it a thin plaiſter. Into this compound you muſt dip ſome fine lint, and you'l find it very uſeful for any angry part; as alſo when one limb preſſes or otherwiſe incommodes another, as happens in hydropical and other ſwollen people, whoſe belly ſo ſinks down, that the thighs ſuffer by it; in which caſe ſuch lints are to be put between the parts, to keep them from immediately touching and preſſing one another.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Gangrene</hi> is cured with Sal-armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niac boiled in Urine, eſpecially in that of the Patient, and clapping ſuch U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine upon the part affected: The quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the Sal-armoniac may be ſix drachms.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:60082:73"/>For <hi>frozen Feet,</hi> take Gander-ſuet and Deer-ſuet; diſſolve them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and pour them into a white ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavated Turnip, and expoſe this for a while to the Air, Rain, Wind, Hoar-froſt, Snow, according as the ſeaſon ſhall be. Then mince the Turnip, and fry it in the ſame Suet which you had poured into it; that done, ſqueeſe it out, and let the fat fall upon cold water; and being there brought to conſiſtence, take it off, and bring it over the helm from burned Wine, and decant this carefully from it again, and 'tis duely prepared. You may alſo recover frozen Feet with white rotten Turnips, beaten with Butter or Tallow, and ſo clapt on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:60082:74"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of ſeveral promiſcuous Medical Practiſes, for the Service of the honeſt Souldier.</head>
               <p>THis Chapter I have annexed to the former as an <hi>Appendix,</hi> for the eaſe and good of Souldiers; wherein ſome things will occurr, not inferiour to thoſe, that have prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But herein I have kept no order, but ſet them down promiſcuouſly, yet faithfully, to ſupply what may have been omitted before.</p>
               <p>If you be troubled with the <hi>Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach,</hi> coming from the cold in winter, take the root of <hi>Pyrethrum</hi> (Pellitory of <hi>Spain</hi>) and boil it in Vineger, and hold this Vineger warm in your mouth, and it will draw out the phlegm that cauſes the pain. Or, take the root of Elder, boil it in half Wine and half Water, and hold it warm upon the Teeth. But what you take of this Decoction muſt be
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60082:74"/>
often ſpit out, and other freſh taken into your mouth; of which I have found wonderful Effects.</p>
               <p>The root of <hi>Heath</hi> boiled together with the ſame herb in wine, and laid on, is eſteem'd to be powerful in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out thorns and ſplinters.</p>
               <p>You may make a good Ointment againſt the <hi>Itch</hi> and <hi>Scabbs,</hi> of <hi>Savin,</hi> ſtale Fat, Brimſtone and Juniper-ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Oyl.</p>
               <p>If your Limbs after a long ſickneſs be weak, boil <hi>Valerian</hi>-roots in Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil-oyl, and anoint ſuch Limbs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Alſo the Oyl of <hi>Lillies in the valley,</hi> and that of <hi>yellow Violets,</hi> is good for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>For worms in the Fingers, bruiſe <hi>Perſicaria</hi> (Arſmart,) and lay it on; or take of a Piggs Bladder of Gall, and put it on the affected Finger like a Thimble.</p>
               <p>If you have any coagulated or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed blood in your Breaſt, make a Decoction of <hi>Scabious, Chervil,</hi> and <hi>Germander,</hi> in two parts of wine, and one part of water; ſtrain it, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60082:75"/>
drink of it mornings and evenings.</p>
               <p>Againſt the putrefaction of the Mouth, make a Decoction of <hi>Privet</hi> in water, adding afterwards a little Allum to it, and uſe it for a gargariſm. Alſo a Decoction of the middle rind of <hi>Hawthorn,</hi> with a little Allum, is of great effect in the ſame caſe.</p>
               <p>Cabbage and Colewort-leaves burnt to aſhes, and a Lixivium made of it, and clapp'd on, cureth a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene, and the wild Fire, eſpecially if you mingle a little Oyl of Elder therewith. If you can have no Elder-bloſſoms for this Oyl, take the green middle rind of Elder, and boil it in Oyl Olive, and then ſtrain the Oyl; which done, take freſh rind of Elder, and proceed with it as before, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it three or four times to make the Oyl the ſtronger. You may add a little wine to it whilſt 'tis boiling, but that muſt all boil away, and ſo long till the Oyl cracks no more in the fire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Southern-wood</hi> ſtamped with greaſe and laid on, draweth out ſplinters.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:60082:75"/>If you have the Itch or are ſcabby, and can light upon ſome water ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the hollowneſs of a <hi>Beech-tree,</hi> waſh your ſelf with it. Or make a Decoction of the brown rind of <hi>Alder,</hi> (which is under the gray,) in Butter, and anoint your ſelf with it; mixing, if you will, a little Brimſtone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>If you be troubled with the <hi>Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm,</hi> or any running Scab, infuſe Litharge in Vineger, and let it ſtand a night infuſed, or make a Decoction of the ſame in Vineger. But your pan or veſſel muſt be of braſs. This Vineger mingle with Oyl of Elder, or of Roſes, or the like, and it will become a fine gray Salve, curing ſuch running Scabs as aforeſaid, and coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alſo Inflammations.</p>
               <p>If your Body be bound, take <hi>Sage</hi> pulveriſed, and mix it with greaſe, and anoint your Navil with the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a haſel-nut of it. This I have with very good ſucceſs adviſed to women in childbed, that were thus bound and obſtructed. If you will
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:60082:76"/>
have it ſtronger, mix with it the Gall of a Fiſh or of any Animal whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; but then you muſt not give it to a woman in childbed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gromel</hi> (by the <hi>Latins</hi> call'd <hi>Milium Solis</hi>) pulveriſed, and the weight of half a ducat of it taken in wine or broath, provoketh urine; yet muſt the belly be open'd firſt. The ſame doth <hi>Linaria</hi> or <hi>Toad-flax,</hi> boiled in wine or broath. Likewiſe diſtilled water of Radiſhes, repeating the diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſeveral times from other freſh Radiſhes. Which will have the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effect, if the Patient bath his lower parts in a bath made of <hi>Marſh-mallows, Melilot,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gromel,</hi> above-mention'd, taken in warm broath, expels the birth: And ſo do the bloſſoms or buds of Walnut-trees; Crabs-eyes alſo, pulveriſed and taken in warm broath; likewiſe <hi>Iſſop</hi> boiled in wine, and drank warm. This I have inſerted for the ſake of poor Souldiers-wives, who amongſt us of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten follow the Camp. If they have any great After-pains, let them bath
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:60082:76"/>
their lower parts in a Bath made of <hi>Dill,</hi> and <hi>Camomil</hi>-flowers. And the yolks of hard Eggs, beaten toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome convenient Oyl (Nut-oyl is the beſt,) and a Plaiſter made of it, and laid to the belly, is alſo very good. If they have too great a profuſion of blood, let them take a drachm of burnt Harts-horn, and burnt Ivory, in a convenient Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle.</p>
               <p>In caſe of a mortal wound, take of pure Turpentine four ounces, waſh it with freſh limpid water, and then diſſolve it over a mild fire; which done, mix with it two ounces or two ounces and an half of white Wax, diſſolved apart: To this add about three ounces of Womans-milk, which is ſucked by a Boy. The Turpentine and Wax being ſomewhat cooled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, muſt be well ſtirr'd, and then powred on cold Vineger; whence, when 'tis brought to a conſiſtence, it is to be taken off, and made into a Plaiſter, and ſo laid on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Horſe-tail</hi> (in <hi>Latin, Equiſetum</hi>) heals
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:60082:77"/>
the wounds in the urinary parts, the powder of it being taken in broath or <hi>Speedwel</hi>-water, or the Decoction thereof being drank.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gummi Ammoniac</hi> is a good diſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of hard Tumors and Knobs: <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camahaca</hi> appeaſeth pain proceeding from cold, being laid on the part affected.</p>
               <p>To make the pellets uſed to be put in wounds that are to be kept open, (which here in <hi>Germany</hi> we call <hi>Quell-maiſſel,</hi>) take a Spunge of the fineſt ſort, put it in Whites of Eggs well beaten and mixed with Roſe-water, to make the ſaid Spunge imbibe this moiſture. Which done, bind it cloſe together with thred, and let it well dry in the Air, and ſo convey of it into the wound that is to be kept open: where it will ſwell again, and ſo diſtend the wound.</p>
               <p>If you be troubled with the <hi>Gonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoea,</hi> take <hi>Houſe-leek</hi> growing on old walls (call'd by the <hi>Latins, Semper vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum minus,</hi>) put it into your ſhoes, and go bare-foot upon it; anoint your
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:60082:77"/>
loyns and privy parts with <hi>Henbane-oyl;</hi> and take mornings the quantity of two big haſel-nuts of well waſhed Turpentine, for ſome days together, avoiding all aromatic, hard, and ſalt meat.</p>
               <p>An old Experimenter hath noted, That whoſoever ſhall waſh his head twice a week with a <hi>Lixivium</hi> made of Juniper-aſhes, his ſight ſhall never fail him, but remain good to his end; nor ſhall that perſon be troubled with any vermin upon his head, nor with any head-ach, nor ſuffer any change of his hair. For my part, I never tryed it; but it being a very plain and ſafe thing, I thought good here to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it.</p>
               <p>Againſt the biting of a Mad-dog, lay <hi>Aſſa fatida</hi> with Garlick upon the bite; it will draw out the venom.</p>
               <p>To free your ſelf from the Gravel, make a Decoction of <hi>Aſh-wood</hi> in wine, and drink of it warm once or twice a day upon an empty ſtomach; uſing withall good baths. <hi>Vervin</hi> alſo, the leaves and roots, beaten together,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:60082:78"/>
and drank, is very good in this caſe.</p>
               <p>If you have a ſtrong breath, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a foul ſtomach, infuſe <hi>Wormwood</hi> and <hi>Carduus benedictus,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome <hi>Citron-peels,</hi> in wine, and let them boil a little therein, and then drink a good draught of it mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. Chew alſo and ſwallow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a little <hi>Myrrh,</hi> and take now and then three or four Aloes-pills.</p>
               <p>I could add many other things, if my leiſure would permit: Theſe which I have ſet down, you will take in good part; and though I have not tryed them all my ſelf, yet you may reſt aſſured, that ſuch as have not been experimented by my ſelf, have been tryed by my honoured Collegues and other honeſt perſons, and approv'd.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:78"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>AIr,</hi> what to be obſerved of it in the Campy <hi>9.</hi> Preſervatives againſt the corruption of the Air, <hi>21, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Animals,</hi> their blood of what efficacy, <hi>45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antonies fire,</hi> how to be allayed, <hi>140, 141.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>BElly,</hi> the cure of the Aches and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and Gripings thereof, <hi>65, 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beer,</hi> new beer cauſes the Strangury, <hi>12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Blood,</hi> how to cure caſting up of blood, <hi>54.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>And the bleeding of the Noſe, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Blood coagulated, how to be helped, <hi>133, 145.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boyls</hi> peſtilential and their cure, <hi>92, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:79"/>
                  <hi>Brick</hi> well burnt good againſt a <hi>Tenaſmus, 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brimſtone</hi> a good Medicine in infectious caſes, <hi>41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bread,</hi> wheaten-bred coming hot out of the oven and dipt in red wine very good againſt Fluxes, <hi>75.</hi> The ſame duely prepared good in peſtilential Sores, <hi>94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bones</hi> broken, how to be order'd, <hi>131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bran</hi> good for wrenching of Limbs, <hi>131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burning,</hi> how to be healed, <hi>137.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>CArbuncles</hi> peſtilential, and their cure, <hi>92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Carlina</hi> good againſt faintneſs, <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chirurgions</hi> of an Army, and their qualities, <hi>14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cold</hi> Nights how to provide againſt, <hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Corns</hi> of the Feet how to be cured, <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cough,</hi> and its cure, <hi>54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crafiſhes</hi> burnt alive good againſt the Bloody-flux, <hi>80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crafiſhes,</hi> after a certain way prepared, of great uſe for drawing out of the body thorns, ſmall-ſhot, <hi>&amp;c. 135.</hi> The ſame
<pb facs="tcp:60082:79"/>
fried in freſh butter allays burning, <hi>141.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crocus Martis</hi> a high Remedy againſt the Bloody-flux, <hi>81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clyſters,</hi> and their uſe in the field, <hi>83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chearfulneſs</hi> good in peſtilential times, <hi>31.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>DAiſie</hi> and its excellency, <hi>13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> in an Army, and their cure, <hi>18, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diet</hi> to be well obſerved in the Camp, <hi>20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drinks</hi> how to provide in the field, <hi>7.</hi> The exceſs of it to be avoided, <hi>12.</hi> The danger of drinking whilſt one is hot, and the care to be taken in that caſe, <hi>12, 13.</hi> Drinks in cold weather, <hi>25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drawing</hi> out of thorns, ſplinters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how to be effected, <hi>135. 145.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dropſie,</hi> and its cure, <hi>72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drought,</hi> how to be remedied, <hi>85.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:80"/>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>EGg-oyl</hi> good for Burnings, <hi>140.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elder-flowers</hi> good in the plague, <hi>24. 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elder-vineger</hi> good to apply to the Heart in the plague, <hi>48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elder-roots,</hi> the Juyce of them purgeth hydropical perſons exceedingly, <hi>73.</hi> But to be uſed with great caution, <hi>ibid.</hi> Boiled <hi>Elder-buds</hi> have the like ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Emollients</hi> in peſtilential Boils, <hi>93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Excrement</hi> of a Gander is powerful in drawing Iron out of the body, <hi>135.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FAintneſs</hi> how to prevent, <hi>6, 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feet</hi> ſweaty how to remedy, <hi>5. Feet</hi> frozen how to recover, <hi>143.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feavers</hi> of all ſorts how to he managed and cured in an Army, <hi>18. 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fluxes,</hi> their ſeveral ſorts and cures, <hi>74.</hi> Of the Bloody-flux in particular, and its cure, <hi>77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:80"/>
                  <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> dryes and clears the Air, <hi>23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fundament,</hi> the cure of its falling down, <hi>88.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>GAngrene</hi> how to cure, <hi>142. 146.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galling</hi> how to cure, <hi>5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Garlick</hi> uſeful in Fluxes by way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, <hi>88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Goat,</hi> good for men to rub at them when the Air is corrupted, <hi>21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Groin</hi> ſwelled how to cure, <hi>74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guts,</hi> the Griping of them how to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>69 — 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Granat-wine</hi> cures the Bloody-flux, <hi>82.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gun-powder</hi> purifies the Air, <hi>23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gum Elemi</hi> of conſiderable uſe in wounds, <hi>129.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gonorrhoea</hi> how to be order'd, <hi>150.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gravel</hi> how to be removed, <hi>151.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>HAwes</hi> cure Fluxes, <hi>76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Harts-horn</hi> good againſt Fluxes, <hi>75.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:81"/>
                  <hi>Hearing</hi> how to be recover'd. <hi>53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heart,</hi> the cure of its Inflammation, <hi>61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haemorrhoid-vein,</hi> the uſe of its blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,<hi>90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Horſes</hi> how to be made vigorous, <hi>7.</hi> Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Horſes, <hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hunger</hi> and Thirſt to be prevented by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain herbs, <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>JAundiſe,</hi> the cauſe and cure of it, <hi>68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Imperatoria</hi> good againſt faintneſs, <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Infection,</hi> its preſervatives and cures, both for the Poor and Rich, <hi>20 — 36.</hi> The Hungarian Infection and its cure, <hi>37, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inflammation,</hi> its ſeveral ſorts and cures, <hi>55 — 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Juniper-wood</hi> burnt, good in times of the plague, <hi>23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Itch</hi> how to be cured, <hi>145, 146.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:60082:81"/>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>LArd,</hi> when freſh very good againſt the Inflammation of the Mouth, <hi>62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lard</hi> good againſt Burnings, <hi>141.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lead</hi> a conſiderable cooler, <hi>61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leggs,</hi> the cure of their ſwelling, <hi>74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liver,</hi> the cure of the Obſtructions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<hi>68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lillies,</hi> the Juyce of the Roots of <hi>blew</hi> Lillies have great vertue of purging hydropical perſons, but to be uſed with great diſcretion, <hi>73.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lapis ſabuloſus</hi> good to heal broken Bones,<hi>131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Luxations</hi> how to be order'd, <hi>131.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>MAriſca's,</hi> and the cure of them, <hi>89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maſtic,</hi> drys and clears the Air, <hi>23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meſaraic-veins,</hi> and the effects of their being obſtructed, <hi>68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Milk</hi> duly prepared good againſt the Bloody-flux, <hi>77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:82"/>
                  <hi>Moſs</hi> of wild Roſe-ſhrubs an approved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in Bloody-fluxes, <hi>78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mouth,</hi> how to remedy the falling down of the Palate of the Mouth, <hi>53.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>NIter</hi> excellent to allay Inflammations, <hi>60.</hi> The way how to prepare it for that uſe, <hi>61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Noſe,</hi> how to remedy the bleeding of it, <hi>54.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OBſtructions</hi> of the Liver, and the cure, <hi>68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oyl of Scorpions</hi> very good to anoint the Heart with in the Plague, <hi>48.</hi> A good <hi>Succedancum</hi> to it deſcribed, <hi>48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oyl of Vitriol</hi> good in Feavers, <hi>51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oaken-leaves</hi> do cure common Fluxes, <hi>76.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>PEſtilential</hi> Diſeaſes and cure, <hi>24, &amp; ſeq. 92, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phyſitians</hi> of an Army and their quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<hi>14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:82"/>
                  <hi>Pear-trees,</hi> the rinds of them cure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fluxes, <hi>76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Preſervatives</hi> fit for Souldiers, <hi>3, 26, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Purgatives</hi> fit Souldiers, <hi>3, 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Putrefaction</hi> the cauſe of grievous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, <hi>38. 65. Putrefaction</hi> of the Mouth how to be cured, <hi>145.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>QUince-wine</hi> good againſt the Bloody-flux, <hi>82.</hi> The ſame extinguiſhes marvellouſly the burning of any ſhot, <hi>138.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>RIng worm,</hi> how to be cured, <hi>146.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ruſt</hi> of Arms how to prevent, <hi>6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rye-biſcuit</hi> duly prepar'd good againſt the Bloody-flux, <hi>80.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>SCarification</hi> and its uſe, <hi>93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Souldiers</hi> Morals, <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Souldiers</hi> care of his body, <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:83"/>
                  <hi>Souldiers</hi> Diſeaſes in the Field; <hi>through the whole Book.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sores</hi> peſtilential and their cure, <hi>92, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spotted</hi> Feavers and their cures, <hi>18, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Squinancy</hi> and its cure, <hi>54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Strangury</hi> and its cure, <hi>12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Surfets</hi> and their cures, <hi>19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swellings</hi> of the Throat and Almonds, how to be cured, <hi>53. 64.</hi> Swelling of the Leggs how to cure, <hi>74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweat</hi> and the ways of procuring it, <hi>33, &amp; ſeq.</hi> See alſo <hi>44, &amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swallows,</hi> burnt to powder, good to thoſe that have been ſhot, <hi>136.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Synovia,</hi> how to be order'd, <hi>137.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>TEnaſmus</hi> and its cure, <hi>86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tench</hi> fried good for Burnings, <hi>137.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirſt,</hi> how to quench in caſe of want of drink, <hi>6.</hi> Thirſt how to quench in Fluxes, <hi>85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Throat</hi> ſwoln how to cure, <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tooth-ach,</hi> its cure, <hi>144.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tongue,</hi> the cure of the Inflammations of it, <hi>55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:83"/>
                  <hi>Turnips,</hi> after a certain way prepared, or rotten, cure frozen feet, <hi>143.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>VErmin</hi> how to remove, <hi>4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vein,</hi> the uſe of the bleeding of the Haemorrhoid-vein, <hi>90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Veſicatories</hi> and their uſe, <hi>93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ulcers</hi> and their cure, <hi>92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vineger</hi> good to waſh the Temples with, in times of the Plague, <hi>24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Venae-ſection</hi> not eaſily to be admitted in peſtilential Diſeaſes, <hi>32, 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vulnerary</hi> Herbs for ſeveral ſorts of Wounds, <hi>132.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVAter,</hi> its differences and choice, <hi>10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wheel-greaſe</hi> a good Ointment for Horſes,<hi>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wind</hi> in the Guts requires keeping the Body ſoluble, <hi>69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worms;</hi> Earth-worms good againſt the Dropſie, together with the way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them, <hi>74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60082:84"/>
                  <hi>Wounds,</hi> their Inflammation how to be prevented, <hi>129.</hi> Their ſwelling how to be helped, <hi>130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wound-drinks</hi> of ſeveral ſorts, <hi>132.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wounds mortal</hi> how to order, <hi>149.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worms</hi> in fingers, how be oured, <hi>145.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wounds</hi> how to be cured, ſee <hi>chap. 10.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
